<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
    xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
    <channel>
        <title>Mildly entertaining</title>
        <link>https://beepb00p.xyz</link>
        <description><![CDATA[feed]]></description>
        <atom:link href="https://beepb00p.xyz/rss.xml" rel="self"
                   type="application/rss+xml" />
        <lastBuildDate>Fri, 05 Jul 2019 00:00:00 UT</lastBuildDate>
        <item>
    <title>How to annotate literally everything</title>
    <link>https://beepb00p.xyz/annotating.html</link>
    <description><![CDATA[<!doctype html>
<html lang="en">
    <head>
        <meta charset="utf-8">
        <meta http-equiv="Content-Type" content="text/html; charset=UTF-8" />
        <meta http-equiv="x-ua-compatible" content="ie=edge">
        <meta name="viewport" content="width=device-width, initial-scale=1">

        <meta name="generator" content="hakyll">
        <meta name="language" content="English">
        
        <meta name="keywords" content="pkm annotation sr tools">
        
        <!-- TODO concat with keywords tags; also need to make comma separated? -->

        <title>How to annotate literally everything | Mildly entertainingᵝ</title>

        <link rel="stylesheet" href="./css/default.css?v=2" />
        <link rel="stylesheet" href="./css/links.css?v=2" />

        <!-- TODO make it conditional on actually having math on page? -->
        <script type="text/javascript">
 window.MathJax = {
     tex2jax: {
         // note that hakyll source has got double dollar signs due to special meaning in templates
         inlineMath: [ ['$','$'], ["\\(","\\)"] ],
         processEscapes: true
     }
 };
</script>
<script async src="https://cdnjs.cloudflare.com/ajax/libs/mathjax/2.7.5/MathJax.js?config=TeX-AMS-MML_HTMLorMML"></script>

    </head>
    <body>
        <header>
            <nav>
                <span class="nav-left">
                    <a class="fat" href="./">Home</a>
                    <!-- TODO eh, not sure if this symbol is good for that... -->
                    ·
                    <a class="fat" href="./ideas.html">Ideas</a>
                    ·
                    <a class="fat" href="./notes.html">Notes</a>
                    ·
                    <a class="fat" href="./tags.html">Tags</a>
                </span>
                <span class="nav-right">
                    <a class="fat" href="./feed.html">Feed</a>
                    ·
                    <a class="fat" href="./site.html">Site</a>
                    ·
                    <a class="fat" href="./me.html">Me</a>
                </span>
            </nav>
        </header>

        <main>
            

<!-- <link rel="stylesheet" href="/css/org.css" /> -->
<link rel="stylesheet" href="./css/org-default.css" />

<link rel="stylesheet" href="./css/org-extra.css?v=2" />



<article>
    <section class="post-title">
    <h1>How to annotate literally everything</h1>
    <div class="summary">Comprehensive overview of existing tools, thoughts on future and interacting with your data</h2>
    </section>
    <!-- are sections appropriate for that? -->

    <section class="content">
    <div id="table-of-contents">
<h2>Table of Contents</h2>
<div id="text-table-of-contents">
<ul>
<li><a href="#org0000003">1. Motivation</a></li>
<li><a href="#org000000c">2. Annotating web</a>
<ul>
<li><a href="#org0000004">Pocket</a></li>
<li><a href="#instapaper">Instapaper</a></li>
<li><a href="#wallabag">Wallabag</a></li>
<li><a href="#hypothesis">Hypothes.is</a></li>
<li><a href="#grasp">Grasp</a></li>
<li><a href="#org000000b">Summary</a></li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><a href="#org0000019">3. Annotating PDFs</a>
<ul>
<li><a href="#org0000010">Okular, Evince, Atril</a></li>
<li><a href="#pdftools">Emacs: pdf-tools</a></li>
<li><a href="#org0000012">Other Linux readers</a></li>
<li><a href="#orgnoter">Emacs: org-noter</a></li>
<li><a href="#xournal">Xournal</a></li>
<li><a href="#hypothesis_pdf">Hypothes.is (again)</a></li>
<li><a href="#polar">Polar</a></li>
<li><a href="#android_ann">Annotating on Android</a></li>
<li><a href="#org0000018">Summary</a></li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><a href="#org0000022">4. Annotating E-ink</a>
<ul>
<li><a href="#kindle">Kindle</a></li>
<li><a href="#kobo">Kobo</a></li>
<li><a href="#koreader">Koreader</a></li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><a href="#org0000028">5. Miscellaneous</a>
<ul>
<li><a href="#org0000023">Annotating paper books</a></li>
<li><a href="#org0000024">Annotating plaintext</a></li>
<li><a href="#org0000025">Annotating videos</a></li>
<li><a href="#org0000026">Other notable mentions</a></li>
<li><a href="#org0000027">Hall of shame!</a></li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><a href="#vision">6. What makes a good annotation system?</a>
<ul>
<li><a href="#comparison">Comparison</a></li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><a href="#infra">7. Using annotation data</a>
<ul>
<li><a href="#org000002b">Extracting reading stats</a></li>
<li><a href="#org000002c">Searching in annotations</a></li>
<li><a href="#org000002d">Providing TODO items</a></li>
<li><a href="#org000002e">Spaced repetition</a></li>
<li><a href="#org000002f">Life log</a></li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><a href="#org0000031">8. --</a></li>
</ul>
</div>
</div>
<p>
TLDR: when I read I try to read <a href="https://help.open.ac.uk/active-reading">actively</a>, which for me mainly involves using various tools to annotate content: highlight and leave notes as I read. I've programmed <a href="#infra">data providers</a> that parse them and provide nice interface to interact with this data from other tools. My <a href="#org0000000">automated scripts</a> use them to render these annotations in human readable and searchable plaintext and generate <a href="#org0000001">TODOs</a>/<a href="#org0000002">spaced repetition</a> items.
</p>

<p>
In this post I'm gonna elaborate on all of that and give some motivation, review of these tools (mainly with the focus on open source thus extendable software) and my vision on how they could work in an ideal world.
I won't try to convince you that my method of reading and interacting with information is superior for you: it doesn't have to be, and there are people out there more eloquent than me who do that. I assume you want this too and wondering about the practical details.
</p>

<div id="outline-container-org0000003" class="outline-2">
<h2 id="org0000003"><span class="section-number-2">1</span> Motivation</h2>
<div class="outline-text-2" id="text-1">
<p>
<aside class="sidenote">For brevity I'll just refer to all of this as 'content' further on</aside>
At some point in my life I realized I didn't remember most of the books/papers/posts/videos I had consumed few years before. 
</p>

<p>
That bothered me increasingly until I bought a Kindle which had 'highlight' functionality and virtual keyboard; and I had discovered it to help a lot with recalling.
</p>

<p>
I've become increasingly obsessed with this and these days ability to highlight when I read serves multiple purposes for me:
</p>

<ul class="org-ul">
<li>the very act of spending conscious effort on highlighting and commenting helps to remember better.</li>
<li><p>
it's easier to recall the content I already read, I just skim through highlights and refresh the memory
</p>

<p>
In particular, often I'd run on something on the internet that I remember reading before. If I have annotations for that, I can quickly go through them and restore the context.
</p></li>
<li>it's easier to recommend content to other people because you can refer to specific moments or points you liked/disliked</li>
<li>it's got social value if highlights are visible to other people (e.g. <a href="#hypothesis">Hypothesis</a>, Medium, Goodreads)</li>
<li>it helps with <a href="./notes.html#book_scoring">book scoring</a>. If I don't have any highlights, it probably means that the content was not interesting at all for me. Fiction books are not an exception: I tend to highlight use of language I liked, inspirational things, etc.</li>
<li>it serves as activity log if you are into <a class="post-tag" href="./tags.html#lifelogging">#lifelogging</a>.</li>
<li>you can <a href="#org0000001">populate your TODO list</a> and <a href="#org0000002">step up your spaced repetition game</a>.</li>
</ul>

<p>
I'm going to review some of the tools I tried using and still using and highlight their different positive and negative aspects. If you're getting impatient, you can skip straight to my <a href="#comparison">comparison table</a>.
</p>
</div>
</div>

<div id="outline-container-org000000c" class="outline-2">
<h2 id="org000000c"><span class="section-number-2">2</span> Annotating web</h2>
<div class="outline-text-2" id="text-2">
</div>
<div id="outline-container-org0000004" class="outline-3">
<h3 id="org0000004"><a href="https://getpocket.com">Pocket</a></h3>
<div class="outline-text-3" id="text-org0000004">
<p>
I won't really write much about it for one reason which is a big deal: while you can highlight text, you can't leave notes. Nearest functionality is 'recommending' a highlight while reading a comment, but that's only displayed on your 'timeline'.
</p>

<p>
Also, interesting enough, <a href="#kobo">Kobo reader</a> has got Pocket integration, but for some reason when you read Pocket articles on Kobo, you can't highlight at all (let alone syncing highlights with Pocket). Not sure what's the purpose of this integration.
</p>

<p>
Pocket was acquired by Mozilla in 2017, which might be a good thing, but so far their main focus seem to be readability features.
</p>
</div>
</div>
<div id="outline-container-org0000006" class="outline-3">
<h3 id="instapaper"><a href="https://www.instapaper.com">Instapaper</a></h3>
<div class="outline-text-3" id="text-instapaper">
<p>
I won't go into Instapaper's readability capabilities (e.g. fonts and article formatting) because it's not something I care much about, so you might be better off googling that for yourself, here I'll concentrate on annotating aspect. 
Here are couple of recent extensive comparisons of Instapaper and Pocket, which feature screenshots and other aspects of Instapaper:
</p>

<ul class="org-ul">
<li><a href="https://zapier.com/blog/instapaper-vs-pocket">Read-It-Later App Showdown: Instapaper vs. Pocket</a>; <a href="https://zappy.zapier.com/A040E0D5-C672-4F08-812B-D7793F6B40A7.png">screenshot</a> of annotation interface.</li>
<li><a href="https://medium.com/@janniks/instapaper-vs-pocket-2019-comparison-453524ff952d">Instapaper vs. Pocket (2019 Comparison)</a></li>
</ul>

<p>
So, to read something in Instapaper, first you'll have to import the article into it (to unclutter and optimize it for reading). 
Due to this import process, you can <b><b>only read and highlight in Instapaper's app</b></b>, and you can only see your highlights there as well, which is its main limitation for me.
</p>

<p>
The only reason I'm using it at all is that its Android app has got <b><b>offline</b></b> capabilities, so I would export to Instapaper things I want to read on the tube while I don't have connection and read/comment while offline.
</p>

<p>
Mind that free version of Instapaper has got <b><b>5 notes per month limit</b></b>. Personally I'm happy to pay 3$ per month for <a href="https://www.instapaper.com/premium">premium version</a> of such a decent product though in absence of good alternatives.
</p>

<p>
Instapaper got <a href="https://www.instapaper.com/api">Json API</a>, through which you can access your saved articles, comments and highlights. I'm using a <a href="https://github.com/karlicoss/instapaper">fork</a> of python wrapper to access it. Highlights are only stored as text though (as opposed to CSS/xpath locators), so there is no easy way to match them against original text apart from some sort of fuzzy search. 
</p>

<p>
<a id="org0000005"></a>Search function works for full text search in saved articles, but doesn't let you restrict search for highlights, and you can't search in notes at all.
</p>

<p>
One red flag was in 2018 when Instapaper wasn't available in Europe for few months until they resolved GDPR issues. While I don't blame it on Instapaper, this is a kind of thing that happens when you don't own your data and use a closed source product.
</p>
</div>
</div>

<div id="outline-container-org0000008" class="outline-3">
<h3 id="wallabag"><a href="https://github.com/wallabag/wallabag">Wallabag</a></h3>
<div class="outline-text-3" id="text-wallabag">
<p>
Wallabag is the most mature open source/selfhosted read-it-later kind of project I know of. <a href="https://opensource.com/article/18/7/wallabag">Here's</a> a review featuring some screenshots of their web app and Android app.
</p>

<p>
It's very similar to Instapaper in terms of <b><b>having to import</b></b> the article in Wallabag in order to annotate it. I used it for a while and only had some issues with importing articles heavy on MathJax backed Latex.
</p>

<p>
If you don't want to selfhost it, you can use <a href="https://www.wallabag.it/en">wallabag.it</a> hosting for as little as 9 euros per year and two weeks of trial.
</p>

<p>
<a id="org0000007"></a>There is also an <a href="https://github.com/wallabag/android-app">Android app</a>, but sadly it <a href="https://github.com/wallabag/android-app/issues/115">lacks</a> support for highlighting.
</p>

<p>
I wish it had more attention from the community, and might try to work on Android annotation when I got more time.
</p>
</div>
</div>
<div id="outline-container-org0000009" class="outline-3">
<h3 id="hypothesis"><a href="https://web.hypothes.is/#see-how-it-works">Hypothes.is</a></h3>
<div class="outline-text-3" id="text-hypothesis">
<p>
Hypothesis is simply awesome and my favorite web annotation tool. Their killer feature is that it embeds a bit of JS in the page to provide an <b><b>in-browser overlay</b></b>, so you don't have to leave the page you were reading and can highlight and add comments natively.
They use something cool called <a href="https://web.hypothes.is/blog/fuzzy-anchoring">fuzzy anchoring</a> to achieve this.
That also makes annotations <b><b>resilient to document markup changes</b></b>, and if they can't locate your annotations it would be still shown in metadata as <a href="https://web.hypothes.is/blog/showing-orphaned-annotations">'orphaned'</a>, so you never lose your notes.
</p>

<p>
Another cool feature is that you can choose to make your annotations public and see other people's annotations or create a private group if you want to share them among specific people only.
</p>

<p>
To get a sense of it you can skim through <a href="https://web.hypothes.is/help/annotation-basics">tutorial</a> which has plenty of screenshots,
and I also strongly recommend you checking it out in action here: <a href="https://web.hypothes.is/blog/annotation-is-now-a-web-standard">Annotation Is Now a Web Standard</a>.
You don't have to install anything or register, it's just a widget embedded in the page, but do make sure to allow JS.
You should see yellow highlights and the sidebar on the right.
</p>

<p>
It's open source, can be selfhosted and they provide their own service for free (but please consider donating them!).
</p>

<p>
Since Hypothesis powered by javascript, it actually works well in modern <b><b>Android</b></b> browsers via <a href="https://web.hypothes.is/start/">bookmarklet</a>.
It's somewhat not obvious in terms of browser UI how to actually use them though:
</p>
<ul class="org-ul">
<li>for mobile Firefox, once you added a bookmarklet, to invoke it you need to <a href="https://www.reddit.com/r/firefox/comments/3uquy5/do_bookmarklets_work_in_firefox_browser_for/cxh8uvq">tap on the address bar</a> and click the bookmarklet.</li>
<li>for mobile Chrome, it's a bit more tedious but also <a href="https://android.stackexchange.com/questions/159308/how-can-a-bookmarklet-be-added-on-mobile-chrome">possible</a>.</li>
</ul>


<p>
One downside of this service is that you won't be able to annotate while offline.
I feel it's actually more of mobile browser's problem in general rather than Hypothesis though.
While you potentially can annotate offline without querying API and preserving data in <code>localStorage</code>, if you can't load the page in the first place, it doesn't matter. Perhaps that can be given better support in browsers.
</p>

<p>
Hypothesis got <a href="https://h.readthedocs.io/en/latest/api-reference/v1/#tag/annotations/paths/~1search/get">JSON API</a> which gives access to your and other people's public annotations.
I'm using <a href="https://github.com/judell/Hypothesis">judell/Hypothesis</a> python wrapper to access and back up this data.
</p>
</div>
</div>

<div id="outline-container-org000000a" class="outline-3">
<h3 id="grasp"><a href="./grasp.html">Grasp</a></h3>
<div class="outline-text-3" id="text-grasp">
<p>
Shameless plug! If you just want to send annotations directly into a plaintext (e.g. org-mode) file and don't really care about displaying them within the original web page you can use my <a href="https://github.com/karlicoss/grasp">grasp</a> browser addon for that.
</p>

<p>
I typically use it for highlights that would be good candidates for TODO items, e.g. something actionable like piece of advice or further reading.
</p>

<p>
Not available for <a href="https://github.com/karlicoss/grasp/issues/15">mobile yet</a>, but perhaps on Android native select and share capabilities (e.g. into <a href="https://github.com/orgzly/orgzly-android">orgzly</a>) makes more sense anyway.
</p>
</div>
</div>

<div id="outline-container-org000000b" class="outline-3">
<h3 id="org000000b">Summary</h3>
<div class="outline-text-3" id="text-org000000b">
<p>
<a href="#hypothesis">Hypothses.is</a> is a clear winner for me on desktop and I'm using <a href="#instapaper">Instapaper</a> for offline reading on Android.
</p>
</div>
</div>
</div>

<div id="outline-container-org0000019" class="outline-2">
<h2 id="org0000019"><span class="section-number-2">3</span> Annotating PDFs</h2>
<div class="outline-text-2" id="text-3">
<p>
<aside class="sidenote">Disclaimer: I don't own a Mac so have no idea what's going on in their world. Sorry!</aside>
PDF format is a complicated beast, and its native annotations are a whole different story to annotating web.
</p>

<p>
First, its ISO standard is <a href="https://www.iso.org/standard/63534.html">not freely available</a>. Adobe website has got some sort of <a href="https://www.adobe.com/devnet/pdf/pdf_reference.html">reference</a>
which is not the same as standard, but apparently close enough.
</p>

<p>
There are quite a few different kinds of PDF annotations, e.g. you can see them here in <a href="https://www.adobe.com/content/dam/acom/en/devnet/pdf/PDF32000_2008.pdf">section 12.5.6: Annotation Types</a> or in <a href="https://gitlab.freedesktop.org/poppler/poppler/blob/a4d3db87c3bae5e2a364c828479a6cbb0277069e/poppler/Annot.h#L606-634">Poppler source code</a>.
In addition to Highlight and Text types there are things like support for styling, underlines, strikethoughs, and even (heaven forbid) sounds, movies and 3D.
</p>

<p>
Using native PDF annotations has one major drawback: you will have to save metadata back to the PDF file at some point.
At worst it could be impossible due to DRM, but in any case, you'd need to somehow remember that some of your documents might have private notes inside.
I get around it by making a copy of the file I'm about to annotate first, and giving it <code>[annotated]</code> prefix so I wouldn't confuse it with the original file.
</p>
</div>

<div id="outline-container-org0000010" class="outline-3">
<h3 id="org0000010">Okular, Evince, Atril</h3>
<div class="outline-text-3" id="text-org0000010">
<p>
Probably most widely used PDF readers, all of these use <a href="https://poppler.freedesktop.org">Poppler</a> library for working with PDF, which in particular does the messy business of annotation handling.
</p>

<p>
All of them would let you view existing annotations, but there are some nuances and limitations:
</p>

<ul class="org-ul">
<li><a href="https://github.com/mate-desktop/atril">Atril</a> (as of 1.20.3) allows you to add or edit popup notes only, other types of annotations aren't even displayed in the sidebar</li>
<li><p>
<a href="https://wiki.gnome.org/Apps/Evince">Evince</a> (as of 3.32.0) only allows to add or edit highlights or popup notes (no inline!). Here is <a href="https://www.debugpoint.com/2016/05/evince-3-18-2-comes-with-text-and-highlight-annotation-in-ubuntu-16-04">article</a> with some screenshot (not much changed since 2016).
</p>

<p>
However it's got a nasty few years old bug (<a href="https://bugs.launchpad.net/ubuntu/+source/evince/+bug/1567565">1</a>, <a href="https://gitlab.gnome.org/GNOME/evince/issues/868">2</a>) that doesn't allow you saving over the same file you're editing. That means that to work around it every time you want to persist your changes, you'd have to save to a new file and reopen the new copy. That makes it pretty unusable unless you only want to do couple of changes.
</p></li>

<li><p>
<a id="org000000d"></a><a href="https://okular.kde.org">Okular</a> (as of 1.6.3) allows <b><b>editing and adding pretty much every type of annotation</b></b> that you would expect: highlights, popup and inline notes, freehand and <a href="https://docs.kde.org/stable5/en/kdegraphics/okular/annotations.html">more</a>.
</p>

<p>
Annotation process (<a href="./annotating/okular.jpg">screenshot</a>) is pretty pleasant, hitting Ctrl-S results in saving the file you're working on without any problems.
</p>

<p>
<a id="org000000e"></a>Okular also got support for something called <a href="https://docs.kde.org/stable5/en/kdegraphics/okular/annotations.html">'document archive'</a>, which saves the original document in a zip file along with <code>metadata.xml</code>, which allows you to <b><b>annotate non-PDF files</b></b> (e.g. DJVU), which is a very neat feature. It's obviously Okular specific, in theory though it's possible to process <code>metadata.xml</code> with other tools.
</p>

<p>
<a id="org000000f"></a>Search in okular can't be restricted to annotations only and while you can use normal PDF search for inline notes and highlights (along with the other text that happened to match), it doesn't work at all for popups.
</p>

<p>
Even though Okular is part of KDE, there is no reason not to use it in other desktops environments, it's not that complicated in terms of UI; looks quite native in GTK, and few extra dependencies are barely a problem these days.
</p></li>
</ul>
</div>
</div>

<div id="outline-container-org0000011" class="outline-3">
<h3 id="pdftools"><a href="https://github.com/politza/pdf-tools#pdf-tools-readme">Emacs: pdf-tools</a></h3>
<div class="outline-text-3" id="text-pdftools">
<p>
Pdf-tools (as of 0.90) is a PDF viewer for Emacs that meant to be more efficient than the builtin one (in terms of rendering), but is also capable of interacting with PDF metadata.
</p>

<p>
Here's a <a href="./annotating/pdf-tools.jpg">screenshot</a> and a short <a href="https://www.dailymotion.com/video/x2bc1is">screencast</a>, interesting stuff starts somewhere around 02:00 mark.
</p>

<p>
One big drawback is that to highlight and add new annotations you <b><b>still have to use mouse</b></b>, which loses half of the benefits of using Emacs for me.
Also it's got some minor issue displaying inline annotations text in the 'Content' buffer and annotations list (you can edit it if you click on it with your mouse though).
</p>
</div>
</div>

<div id="outline-container-org0000012" class="outline-3">
<h3 id="org0000012">Other Linux readers</h3>
<div class="outline-text-3" id="text-org0000012">
<p>
There are few other apps I tried using so figured it's worth mentioning.   
</p>

<ul class="org-ul">
<li><p>
<a href="https://mupdf.com">mupdf</a> (as of 1.14.0) is both rendering library (claimed to be faster than poppler) and PDF viewers. It's capable of displaying all types of highlights and annotations, but there is no way to add or edit them.
</p>

<p>
It mentions annotation editing in <a href="https://mupdf.com/release_history.html">changelog</a>, but in something called 'mupdf-gl', and it doesn't seem to be available in Ubuntu.
</p></li>

<li><a href="https://wiki.archlinux.org/index.php/Zathura">zathura</a> (as of 0.4.3) is capable of both poppler and mupdf backends, but suffers from the same problem that you can't edit and add new highlights. It's pretty sad, because I like it as a viewer: it's minimalist and capable of VI style keybindings.</li>
</ul>
</div>
</div>

<div id="outline-container-org0000013" class="outline-3">
<h3 id="orgnoter"><a href="https://github.com/weirdNox/org-noter">Emacs: org-noter</a></h3>
<div class="outline-text-3" id="text-orgnoter">
<p>
Org-noter (as of 1.3.0) allows you to annotate a PDF while keeping the text annotations in a separate <code>org</code> file which keep track of PDF locations in Org note properties.
<a href="https://github.com/weirdNox/org-noter#screencast">Here's</a> a short demo.
</p>

<p>
For me the main drawback is that it <b><b>doesn't let you highlight</b></b>, which I tend to do a lot.
</p>

<p>
Existing annotations in PDF can be imported via <a href="https://github.com/weirdNox/org-noter/blob/920798e2a977ca74b77cf728ee40bb48450f941b/org-noter.el#L1455"><code>org-noter-create-skeleton</code></a> function (it didn't work for me for some reason though, and I wasn't motivated enough to investigate).
</p>
</div>
</div>

<div id="outline-container-org0000014" class="outline-3">
<h3 id="xournal"><a href="https://github.com/xournalpp/xournalpp#xournal">Xournal</a></h3>
<div class="outline-text-3" id="text-xournal">
<p>
Xournal is different from the above PDF viewers, since it isn't using types of annotations described in the PDF standard and instead uses its own <a href="http://xournal.sourceforge.net/manual.html#tools">tools</a>.
</p>

<p>
It doesn't modify the original files and instead keeps <code>.xoj</code> file containing the metadata and pointing at the original PDF, so in that sense it's pretty similar to <a href="#org000000e">okular</a>. Similarly, it's xournal-specific and can't be viewed anywhere else unless you export it in PDF before sharing (at which point your annotations wold basically become background images).
</p>
</div>
</div>

<div id="outline-container-org0000015" class="outline-3">
<h3 id="hypothesis_pdf"><a href="https://web.hypothes.is/#see-how-it-works">Hypothes.is</a> (again)</h3>
<div class="outline-text-3" id="text-hypothesis_pdf">
<p>
Already mentioned in the previous section, it's also capable of annotating PDFs via <a href="https://github.com/mozilla/pdf.js">pdf.js</a>. 
</p>

<p>
Check out <a href="https://web.hypothes.is/help/annotating-locally-saved-pdfs">their guide</a>, especially if you're using Chrome, apart from it it's as easy as opening the PDF in your browser and activating Hypothesis.
It fingerprints the PDFs so you don't have to worry about losing your annotations and it's easy to collaborate with other people.
</p>

<p>
It seems to work fast enough for big PDF books as well, however generally reading long things in browser is not very convenient as you lose reading position if you close the tab.
</p>
</div>
</div>

<div id="outline-container-org0000016" class="outline-3">
<h3 id="polar"><a href="https://github.com/burtonator/polar-bookshelf#polar-bookshelf">Polar</a></h3>
<div class="outline-text-3" id="text-polar">
<p>
Polar is a new project which aims to be not just reader, but 'personal knowledge repository'. 
</p>

<ul class="org-ul">
<li>supports <a href="https://getpolarized.io/#integrated-annotations">highlights and comments</a></li>
<li><a href="https://getpolarized.io/assets/screenshots/document-repo-2019-04.webp">document repository</a>, so you have overview of all the stuff you ever read/commented. It also keeps track of your reading position.</li>
<li>the <b><b>PDFs are fingerprinted</b></b>, so you don't need to worry about moving them around your filesystem</li>
<li><code>~.polar</code> directory holds all the data, which makes it <b><b>easy to share among your computers</b></b> (e.g. via git, or if you keep it on Dropbox and symlink)</li>
<li>metadata is in well structured <code>json</code> files, which makes it easy to access from scripts</li>
<li>highlight locators keep <a href="https://github.com/burtonator/polar-bookshelf/blob/ac36e59e98d378e1ff7ab02aa241b89fdbb68c46/web/js/metadata/TextHighlightsTest.ts#L164">matched text</a> alongside the absolute coordinates, which leaves potential for matching against different editions of the PDF file</li>
<li>it's got <a href="https://github.com/burtonator/polar-bookshelf#personal-knowledge-repository">builtin flashcards engine</a>. Personally, I'm too used to <a href="https://orgmode.org/worg/org-contrib/org-drill.html">org-drill</a> now, but that's a great a way of introducing <b><b>spaced repetition</b></b> to people.</li>
<li>the author is very passionate about this project, invests a lot of effort and quite <a href="https://getpolarized.io/2019/04/11/Polar-Initial-Crowdfunding-Campaign.html">ambitious</a></li>
</ul>

<p>
If you like it, please consider donating them!
</p>

<p>
The only downside is that annotation format is <b><b>Polar specific</b></b>, so it'd be hard to share with other people unless they are willing to use Polar as well.
</p>
</div>
</div>

<div id="outline-container-org0000017" class="outline-3">
<h3 id="android_ann">Annotating on Android</h3>
<div class="outline-text-3" id="text-android_ann">
<ul class="org-ul">
<li><p>
<a href="https://play.google.com/store/apps/details?id=com.adobe.reader">Adobe Reader</a>
</p>

<p>
Supports most reasonable ways of annotation: highlights, popup/inline comments, strikethough, styling, etc. (<a href="./annotating/adobe-annot.jpg">screenshot</a>). "Comment List" gives overview of your document: <a href="./annotating/adobe-list.jpg">screenshot</a>.
</p>

<p>
It offers Adobe Cloud and Dropbox integration, but I rely on Syncthing for syncing my stuff anyway.
</p></li>

<li><p>
<a href="https://play.google.com/store/apps/details?id=com.xodo.pdf.reader">Xodo</a>
</p>

<p>
Basically supports same things that Adobe does.
</p>

<p>
For me, Xodo wins by a very thin margin because its interface tends to be a bit more denser and 'material': <a href="./annotating/xodo-annot.jpg">interface</a>, <a href="./annotating/xodo-list.jpg">annotations list</a>. Otherwise, it's virtually no different from Adobe Reader.
</p></li>

<li><p>
<a href="https://f-droid.org/en/packages/com.artifex.mupdf.viewer.app">mupdf</a>
</p>

<p>
The F-droid description claims it supports annotation, but it couldn't display any of the existing ones in my pdf files. What's more, the app wasn't responsive on any long taps or my attempts to select text, let alone highlight or comment.
</p>

<p>
Perhaps PDF 1.7 is too outdated? Something weird has been going on with the 'full' version, maybe this is somehow related (<a href="https://forum.f-droid.org/t/what-happened-to-mupdf-full-version/4511">1</a>, <a href="https://gitlab.com/fdroid/fdroiddata/issues/252">2</a>).
</p></li>

<li><a href="https://github.com/cgogolin/penandpdf">Pen&amp;Pdf</a>: I tried this one since it was open source and claimed to support annotation, but it didn't even manage to pick up any of the existing ones.</li>
</ul>
</div>
</div>

<div id="outline-container-org0000018" class="outline-3">
<h3 id="org0000018">Summary</h3>
<div class="outline-text-3" id="text-org0000018">
<p>
If you want the convenience of editing and viewing on phone and working with other people, <b><b>Okular</b></b> wins on desktop and <b><b>Adobe Reader/Xodo</b></b> could be used on your phone.
</p>

<p>
If you care about preserving the original PDF files and want convenience in accessing the annotations programmatically, <b><b>Polar</b></b> is best.
</p>
</div>
</div>
</div>

<div id="outline-container-org0000022" class="outline-2">
<h2 id="org0000022"><span class="section-number-2">4</span> Annotating E-ink</h2>
<div class="outline-text-2" id="text-4">
<p>
Two e-ink readers that support highlights and notes I know of are Kindle (I had Paperwhite 2) and Kobo (I own Kobo Aura One).
Highlighting works as you would expect on E-ink touchscreen (long press and dragging the selection); and you can leave notes by typing on a virtual keyboard (somewhat laggy, but ok for up to few sentences).
Perhaps the only differences are how you can search and access the annotations.
</p>
</div>

<div id="outline-container-org000001d" class="outline-3">
<h3 id="kindle">Kindle</h3>
<div class="outline-text-3" id="text-kindle">
<p>
Kindle stores bookmarks, notes and highlights in <code>My Clippings.txt</code> on the device.
The good thing about the format is that it's already plaintext and fairly human readable, so you might be happy with that alone.
The format is a bit nasty for parsing (as you would expect from something with <code>.txt</code> extension). Dates are locale dependent, document locators may or may not have roman numerals, separators are inconsistent at times, etc. 
When I was using Kindle I was just copying the file from time to time, and you can set up some sort of automatic copying when your device is connected similarly to  what I'm doing with <a href="#org000001a">Kobo</a>.
</p>

<p>
Kindle uploads your notes and highlights to <a href="https://read.amazon.com">Kindle Cloud Reader</a>
(<a href="https://www.epubor.com/images/uppic/manage-kindle-highlights-and-notes.png">screenshot</a>, <a href="https://ebookfriendly.com/wp-content/uploads/2017/06/New-home-for-Kindle-highlights-and-notes-540x388.jpg">screenshot</a>)
, but it <b><b>only</b></b> works for stuff bought on Kindle store. <a href="https://www.reddit.com/r/kindle/comments/6sttez/the_new_amazon_highlights_system">Reportedly</a> people also have issues displaying their highlights on Cloud Reader due to copyright restrictions.
</p>

<p>
<a id="org000001b"></a>Kindle also <a href="https://www.makeuseof.com/tag/share-kindle-notes-highlights-friends">integrates with Goodreads</a>, which synchronizes reading progress and lets you selectively share annotations to Goodreads.
But that's also restricted to books bought from Amazon.
</p>

<p>
<a id="org000001c"></a>Search function is somewhat limited: you can search in the book and it displays your highlights alongside content it found in the book, but you can't restrict search to highlights. You can't search in notes either.
Funny enough though, the <code>My Clipping.txt</code> file can be opened on Kindle itself (as any other <code>txt</code> file), and then you can search in it. It's not super convenient, but better than nothing. (I wasn't brave enough to try and see what happens if you try to highlight in this file.)
</p>
</div>
</div>

<div id="outline-container-org0000020" class="outline-3">
<h3 id="kobo">Kobo</h3>
<div class="outline-text-3" id="text-kobo">
<p>
Stores all of it's stuff in <code>.kobo/KoboReader.sqlite</code> on the device.
</p>

<p>
<a id="org000001e"></a>The database has got lots of cool stuff: in addition to highlights and notes you can also access reading progress, time spend reading and possibly some other interesting data I didn't manage to reverse engineer yet.
You can check out <a href="https://github.com/karlicoss/kobuddy">kobuddy</a>, which is my attempt to extract useful data from the database and provide nicer high level Python interface. It's also fairly straightforward to open it in <code>sqlitebrowser</code> and play with your own queries.
</p>

<p>
<a id="org000001a"></a>Kobo <b><b>doesn't seem to support cloud sync for annotations</b></b>. I was considering syncing the database wirelessly, as <a href="https://github.com/dropmeaword/kobo-aura-remote">there are</a> some SSH modules for its firmware, but people report it <a href="https://github.com/dropmeaword/kobo-aura-remote/issues/1">may break wifi</a> on it. So I figured it's not worth the trouble and using <a href="https://github.com/karlicoss/kobuddy/blob/master/scripts/backup.py">this script</a> which runs in cron every minute and tries to backup the database from device. I might add it to udev rules at some point, but it's worked well enough so far.
</p>

<p>
<a id="org000001f"></a>There is an official <a href="https://play.google.com/store/apps/details?id=com.kobobooks.android">Android app</a> which lets you manage and annotate books from Kobo store and seems to be syncing progress between eink and phone.
However annotations <b><b>don't sync between Kobo and phone</b></b> for me, and other people also report same experience: <a href="https://www.mobileread.com/forums/showthread.php?t=314687">1</a>, <a href="https://www.mobileread.com/forums/showthread.php?t=256685">2</a>, <a href="https://www.mobileread.com/forums/showthread.php?t=271762">3</a>. 
<a href="https://www.mobileread.com/forums/showthread.php?p=3056862#post3056862">Some</a> claim it works on iphones though.
</p>

<p>
Kobo lets you conveniently search over all of your highlights and notes.
</p>
</div>
</div>

<div id="outline-container-org0000021" class="outline-3">
<h3 id="koreader"><a href="https://github.com/koreader/koreader#main-features-for-users">Koreader</a></h3>
<div class="outline-text-3" id="text-koreader">
<p>
Koreader is an alternative <b><b>open source</b></b> software for Kindle, Kobo and other E-ink devices.
</p>

<p>
It's got some very cool <a href="https://github.com/koreader/koreader/wiki/Features-list">features</a>, in particular most common document formats, dictionary and Wikipedia lookups, and various plugins.
</p>

<p>
It also supports highlighting, but (as of v2019.06), note taking is unsupported <a href="https://github.com/koreader/koreader/issues/1095">yet</a>, but some progress is going on. I'd be keen to try it once it's implemented!
</p>
</div>
</div>
</div>


<div id="outline-container-org0000028" class="outline-2">
<h2 id="org0000028"><span class="section-number-2">5</span> Miscellaneous</h2>
<div class="outline-text-2" id="text-5">
</div>
<div id="outline-container-org0000023" class="outline-3">
<h3 id="org0000023">Annotating paper books</h3>
<div class="outline-text-3" id="text-org0000023">
<p>
So far, for me the only downside of using nice tools for annotating digital content is that it ruined the experience of reading paper books for me. 
</p>

<p>
Usually I don't own the books I read, so using a highlighter or pencil would be just mean to the owner.
Even if you own the book and okay with that, it's still not searchable and not easily accessible, which feels very wrong to me.
</p>

<p>
To get around this I've tried few of tricks:
</p>

<ul class="org-ul">
<li>Take pictures of bits I'm interested in, perhaps highlight using image editor on the phone</li>
<li>Sticky notes are ok for commenting as long as you don't damage the book with the glue, but they down help with highlighting</li>
<li><p>
Using paper strips as an annotation overlay.
</p>

<p>
This one I'm particularly proud of coming up to as I haven't found anyone else doing that, and I rarely come up with useful meatspace things.
</p>

<p>
This is how it looks in action: <a href="./annotating/paper-strips.jpg">photo</a>.
</p>

<p>
Basically, before reading, I prepare a bunch of paper strips slightly longer than the page height, kinda like bookmarks.
You will use it as a 'sidebar overlay' for writing notes and highlighting, so the width depends on your handwriting and how much you're expected to do that, I usually use something like 1/4 of the page.
</p>

<p>
If you want to annotate the page, you'll align strip's bottom to the bottom of the page and mark lines you found interesting on this strip and write comments on it as well. You can also use the other side of the strip to annotate the other page.
</p>

<p>
The downside of this is that in order to annotations to make sense, it requires a physical copy of exact same book.
Another one is that it doesn't have automatic timestamps, which somewhat bothers my <a class="post-tag" href="./tags.html#lifelogging">#lifelogging</a> OCD. You can get around it by writing down time as well, but that's quite distracting.
</p></li>
</ul>

<p>
When I'm done with a book, I'd spend a bit of time digitizing annotations and manually typing them into plaintext. Luckily, I don't have to do that often.
</p>
</div>
</div>

<div id="outline-container-org0000024" class="outline-3">
<h3 id="org0000024">Annotating plaintext</h3>
<div class="outline-text-3" id="text-org0000024">
<p>
Often, I want to leave a quick comment to an org-mode item.
I've got a handy Emacs <a href="https://gitlab.com/karlicoss/dotspacemacs/blob/3f14fd054cef1ff95f6a376523cfae9bd1afe22b/init.el#L1019-1027">binding</a> which appends a child note with a timestamp and enters edit mode, so the whole process is smooth.
If you're not using org-mode you still can benefit from something similar, most of modern text editors allow you binding snippets on hotkeys.
</p>

<p>
One big drawback with Org mode (and I believe most of outline/task list formats) though is that if you insert child outline items in the middle of text,
it would structurally break it in two parts, so you'd have to append your commend to the end of current outline (which can be potentially very long).
On the other hand, plain list items, which you can insert in arbitrary place, are very limited and don't support most of things outline support like tags, timestamps, priorities etc.
</p>
</div>
</div>

<div id="outline-container-org0000025" class="outline-3">
<h3 id="org0000025">Annotating videos</h3>
<div class="outline-text-3" id="text-org0000025">
<p>
Often when I watch lectures or some talks on Youtube or in VLC, I want to leave a bookmark or write a note with a reference to a specific timestamp. 
This is pretty much not possible apart from opening your text editor and manually recording the position in video. All the video annotation software I know of is more oriented towards video editing/effects etc.
</p>

<p>
So, if I'm watching something in browser, I normally end up using <a href="#grasp">grasp</a> and manually type the timestamp.
</p>

<p>
This is distracting, but even worse is that whatever you use have no means of quickly jumping to the timestamp you recorded; you'd have to move the slider to it manually. 
</p>

<p>
There is no common standard that I know of for jumping at a certain timestamp neither in web nor in desktop applications (e.g. via mime handler).
</p>

<p>
I'd say this is somewhat unsolved problem, which is surprising since presumably it could be helpful for lots of students.
</p>
</div>
</div>


<div id="outline-container-org0000026" class="outline-3">
<h3 id="org0000026">Other notable mentions</h3>
<div class="outline-text-3" id="text-org0000026">
<p>
Due to the lack of common standard for annotated content, some services try to implement their own:
</p>

<ul class="org-ul">
<li><p>
<a href="https://medium.com/@wiobyrne/getting-started-in-medium-reading-annotating-commenting-and-recommending-757f43be83ee">Medium</a>. They use   highlights and annotation that also serve social function: when you read a Medium post you can see if a certain bit of text was highlighted by many other people.
</p>

<p>
They don't tamper with browser selection, so you can still use external annotation tools like Hypothesis. However, judging by their <a href="https://github.com/Medium/medium-api-docs#3-resources">API</a>, there is no way to access your highlights. Anyway, I would encourage people not to use these especially if you only care about personal use, after all Medium is not the only source of information out there.
</p></li>
</ul>
</div>
</div>

<div id="outline-container-org0000027" class="outline-3">
<h3 id="org0000027">Hall of shame!</h3>
<div class="outline-text-3" id="text-org0000027">
<p>
These are services that wouldn't let you select text. Not sure why that happens: could be some sort of copyright restriction, being assholes, or just accidental pointless restriction.
</p>

<ul class="org-ul">
<li><a href="https://www.quora.com/How-do-I-copy-text-from-Facebook-and-paste-somewhere-else-on-Android-mobile">Facebook</a>: Android app and mobile site prevent text selection.</li>
<li><p>
<a href="https://www.blinkist.com">Blinkist</a>: Android app and website.
</p>

<p>
You can't use native text selection as Blinkist forces some custom JS for highlighting. But their highlights suck: you can't leave a comment and also they actively prevent you from selecting text forcing to use their own JS thing.
</p>

<p>
In addition you can't even export your highlights, best you can do seems to be <a href="https://www.blinkist.com/en/nc/settings/external_services">syncing to an Evernote notebook</a>, and perhaps then you can use Evernote API. I didn't bother with it though.
</p></li>
</ul>
</div>
</div>
</div>

<div id="outline-container-org000002a" class="outline-2">
<h2 id="vision"><span class="section-number-2">6</span> What makes a good annotation system?</h2>
<div class="outline-text-2" id="text-vision">
<p>
In my quest for the perfect annotation engine I've figured certain aspects that make or would make an annotation tool pleasant to use.
</p>

<ul class="org-ul">
<li><p>
<b><b>Uniform</b></b>
</p>

<p>
Highlighting a piece of content and leaving a comment are fairly straightforward operations, and you shouldn't have to think much about how exactly you do it and which program you use.
Most current annotation engines are also somewhat tedious to interact with, add more content in existing annotaions, link, etc.
</p>

<p>
Solving this requires the tools being <b><b>cross platform</b></b> and <b><b>cross format</b></b>.
</p>

<p>
<a href="#hypothesis">Hypothes.is</a> is the move in the right direction, but there are plenty of other things starting from unsupported formats and working offline to paper books which are missed out.
</p>

<p>
While current sad state of different tools/products for different forms of content is understandable, ideally it should be be <b><b>format agnostic</b></b> with some proper way of
<b><b>fingerprinting</b></b> content. If humans can tell whether a novel published online as HTML and a paper novel are the same thing, so can software.
</p>

<p>
Common standard (e.g. <a href="https://www.w3.org/TR/2017/REC-annotation-model-20170223">Web Annotation Data Model</a>) is a good start, but even this one is pretty unknown and not widely accepted.
</p>

<p>
Perhaps in the near future we could exploit existing (fairly robust) OCR technologies and augmented reality to develop a universal annotation tool, but so far that's a whole different ballpark.
</p></li>
</ul>


<ul class="org-ul">
<li><p>
<b><b>Ease of interaction</b></b>
</p>

<p>
Annotating is meant to augment your limited memory capabilities and using them should be <b><b>as easy as retrieving information from your brain</b></b>.
</p>

<p>
While brain-computer interfaces are not quite there, even with existing technologies you can achieve that with as little as few seconds lag just by using
plaintext representations, indexing and incremental search.
</p>

<p>
Personally, I'm solving this problem via <a href="#org0000000">orger</a>.
</p></li>

<li><p>
<b><b>Separate metadata</b></b>
</p>

<p>
Annotations layer should be loosely coupled to the underlying content. If it's not the case, it makes you too dependent on the specific tools, makes harder to keep track of your private data and to share data with other tools.
</p>

<p>
For physical sources of information it matters even more; although they might decline completely in few decades, who knows.
</p>

<p>
Good examples of this approach are <a href="#polar">Polar</a> and <a href="#hypothesis">Hypothesis</a> which keep metadata in well defined format with locators.
</p></li>

<li><p>
<b><b>Data ownership and resilience</b></b>
</p>

<p>
If annotations make essential part of your knowledge, you want to be capable of accessing them <b><b>anytime</b></b>.
</p>

<p>
Ideally everything should work while fully offline without relying on any services.
</p>

<p>
Currently it's not always feasible due to technical complications (e.g. having to selfhost), but this is a good value to pursue.
</p></li>

<li><p>
<b><b>Social and collaborative</b></b>
</p>

<p>
Annotations are a valuable tool for collaborative learning and research, and improving tools can make these activities more pleasant.
</p>

<p>
Blog comments seem to be somewhat in decline which is understandable since it's too annoying to register here and there.
On the other hand, platforms like Facebook comments or Disqus are not very privacy friendly, don't give access to data stored (e.g. if Disqus disappears tomorrow so do comments in your blog),
and are not very friendly towards people who do want to comment anonymously.
</p>

<p>
Perhaps in some near future we could <b><b>ditch all the internet commenting platforms</b></b> and rely on annotation layer instead.
<a href="#hypothesis">Hypothesis</a> basically lets you do that already, perhaps with a little work on design (sidebar is not necessarily convenient for social commenting), it could serve that purpose.
</p>

<p>
I also consider comments people write as projections of their minds and it would be great to give other people easier access to that to get to know each other better.
</p>

<p>
It's hardly worth mentioning that one should be in control whether highlights they are making are private or everyone else can see them.
</p></li>

<li><p>
<b><b>Open source</b></b>: not sure if that even needs justifying :)
</p>

<p>
People have somewhat different requirements for their cognitive tools and it should be possible to can hack them and fix annoying bugs.
That also gives way more potential for integrating them with other services.
</p></li>
</ul>
</div>

<div id="outline-container-org0000029" class="outline-3">
<h3 id="comparison">Comparison</h3>
<div class="outline-text-3" id="text-comparison">
<p>
I'm only listing tools that support proper highlighting and commenting.
</p>

<table border="2" cellspacing="0" cellpadding="6" rules="groups" frame="hsides">


<colgroup>
<col class="org-left">
</colgroup>

<colgroup>
<col class="org-left">

<col class="org-left">

<col class="org-left">

<col class="org-left">

<col class="org-left">

<col class="org-left">
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th scope="col" class="org-left">&nbsp;</th>
<th scope="col" class="org-left">mobile annotations</th>
<th scope="col" class="org-left">fingerprinting</th>
<th scope="col" class="org-left">search in annotations</th>
<th scope="col" class="org-left">separate metadata</th>
<th scope="col" class="org-left">sharing</th>
<th scope="col" class="org-left">open source</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td class="org-left"><a href="#instapaper">Instapaper</a></td>
<td class="org-left"><span style="color:green">Y</span>, offline</td>
<td class="org-left">n/a</td>
<td class="org-left"><span style="color:red">N</span><a href="#org0000005">&uarr;</a></td>
<td class="org-left"><span style="color:red">N</span></td>
<td class="org-left"><span style="color:red">N</span></td>
<td class="org-left"><span style="color:red">N</span></td>
</tr>

<tr>
<td class="org-left"><a href="#wallabag">Wallabag</a></td>
<td class="org-left"><span style="color:red">N</span><a href="#org0000007">&uarr;</a></td>
<td class="org-left">n/a</td>
<td class="org-left"><a href="https://github.com/wallabag/wallabag/issues/3635"><span style="color:red">N</span></a></td>
<td class="org-left"><span style="color:red">N</span></td>
<td class="org-left"><a href="https://github.com/wallabag/wallabag/issues/679"><span style="color:red">N</span></a></td>
<td class="org-left"><span style="color:green">Y</span></td>
</tr>

<tr>
<td class="org-left"><a href="#hypothesis"><b><b>Hypothesis</b></b></a></td>
<td class="org-left"><span style="color:green">Y</span></td>
<td class="org-left"><span style="color:green">Y</span></td>
<td class="org-left"><span style="color:green">Y</span></td>
<td class="org-left"><span style="color:green">Y</span></td>
<td class="org-left"><span style="color:green">Y</span>, web API</td>
<td class="org-left"><span style="color:green">Y</span></td>
</tr>

<tr>
<td class="org-left"><a href="#grasp">Copy-paste</a></td>
<td class="org-left"><span style="color:green">Y</span>, offline</td>
<td class="org-left"><span style="color:red">N</span> (manual)</td>
<td class="org-left"><span style="color:green">Y</span></td>
<td class="org-left"><span style="color:green">Y</span></td>
<td class="org-left"><span style="color:green">Y</span>, file sync</td>
<td class="org-left"><span style="color:green">Y</span></td>
</tr>
</tbody>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td class="org-left"><a href="#org000000d">Okular</a></td>
<td class="org-left">n/a</td>
<td class="org-left"><span style="color:red">N</span></td>
<td class="org-left"><span style="color:#ff9933">limited</span><a href="#org000000f">&uarr;</a></td>
<td class="org-left"><span style="color:#ff9933">limited</span><a href="#org000000e">&uarr;</a></td>
<td class="org-left"><span style="color:green">Y</span>, file sync</td>
<td class="org-left"><span style="color:green">Y</span></td>
</tr>

<tr>
<td class="org-left"><a href="#pdftools">Emacs pdf-tools</a></td>
<td class="org-left">n/a</td>
<td class="org-left"><span style="color:red">N</span></td>
<td class="org-left"><span style="color:red">N</span></td>
<td class="org-left"><span style="color:red">N</span></td>
<td class="org-left"><span style="color:green">Y</span>, file sync</td>
<td class="org-left"><span style="color:green">Y</span></td>
</tr>

<tr>
<td class="org-left"><a href="#orgnoter">Emacs org-noter</a></td>
<td class="org-left"><span style="color:red">N</span></td>
<td class="org-left"><span style="color:red">N</span></td>
<td class="org-left"><span style="color:green">Y</span></td>
<td class="org-left"><span style="color:green">Y</span></td>
<td class="org-left"><span style="color:green">Y</span>, file sync</td>
<td class="org-left"><span style="color:green">Y</span></td>
</tr>

<tr>
<td class="org-left"><a href="#hypothesis_pdf">Hypothesis (PDF)</a></td>
<td class="org-left"><span style="color:red">N</span></td>
<td class="org-left"><span style="color:green">Y</span></td>
<td class="org-left"><span style="color:green">Y</span></td>
<td class="org-left"><span style="color:green">Y</span></td>
<td class="org-left"><span style="color:green">Y</span>, web API</td>
<td class="org-left"><span style="color:green">Y</span></td>
</tr>

<tr>
<td class="org-left"><a href="#xournal">Xournal</a></td>
<td class="org-left"><span style="color:red">N</span></td>
<td class="org-left"><span style="color:red">N</span></td>
<td class="org-left"><span style="color:red">N</span></td>
<td class="org-left"><span style="color:green">Y</span></td>
<td class="org-left"><span style="color:green">Y</span>, file sync</td>
<td class="org-left"><span style="color:green">Y</span></td>
</tr>

<tr>
<td class="org-left"><a href="#polar"><b><b>Polar</b></b></a></td>
<td class="org-left"><span style="color:red">N</span>, <a href="https://github.com/burtonator/polar-bookshelf/issues/916">on roadmap</a></td>
<td class="org-left"><span style="color:green">Y</span></td>
<td class="org-left"><a href="https://github.com/burtonator/polar-bookshelf/issues/966"><span style="color:red">N</span></a></td>
<td class="org-left"><span style="color:green">Y</span></td>
<td class="org-left"><span style="color:green">Y</span>, file sync, cloud</td>
<td class="org-left"><span style="color:green">Y</span></td>
</tr>

<tr>
<td class="org-left"><a href="#android_ann">Xodo/Adobe Reader</a></td>
<td class="org-left"><span style="color:green">Y</span>, offline</td>
<td class="org-left"><span style="color:red">N</span></td>
<td class="org-left"><span style="color:red">N</span></td>
<td class="org-left"><span style="color:red">N</span></td>
<td class="org-left"><span style="color:green">Y</span>, file sync, cloud</td>
<td class="org-left"><span style="color:red">N</span></td>
</tr>
</tbody>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td class="org-left"><a href="#kindle">Kindle</a></td>
<td class="org-left"><span style="color:red">N</span></td>
<td class="org-left"><span style="color:red">N</span></td>
<td class="org-left"><span style="color:#ff9933">limited</span><a href="#org000001c">&uarr;</a></td>
<td class="org-left"><span style="color:green">Y</span></td>
<td class="org-left"><span style="color:#ff9933">limited</span><a href="#org000001b">&uarr;</a></td>
<td class="org-left"><span style="color:red">N</span>, <a href="#koreader">but koreader &uarr;</a></td>
</tr>

<tr>
<td class="org-left"><a href="#kobo"><b><b>Kobo</b></b></a></td>
<td class="org-left"><span style="color:red">N</span>, <a href="#org000001f">broken&uarr;</a></td>
<td class="org-left"><span style="color:red">N</span></td>
<td class="org-left"><span style="color:green">Y</span></td>
<td class="org-left"><span style="color:green">Y</span></td>
<td class="org-left"><span style="color:red">N</span>, <a href="#org000001a">but possible&uarr;</a></td>
<td class="org-left"><span style="color:red">N</span>, <a href="#koreader">but koreader&uarr;</a></td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</div>
</div>
</div>

<div id="outline-container-org0000030" class="outline-2">
<h2 id="infra"><span class="section-number-2">7</span> Using annotation data</h2>
<div class="outline-text-2" id="text-infra">
<p>
Considering there are multiple tools I have to use none of which is fully capable of doing everything I would ideally want from annotation system, I've developed my ways of getting closer to my <a href="#vision">ideal</a>.
For that I've got some infrastructure set up.
</p>

<p>
<b><b>Backups</b></b>: I've already mentioned script I'm using to back up Kobo database, for cloud services I'm running bunch of daily cron jobs that query APIs for data. Most of the job scripts are fairly ad-hoc and just a matter of GET query with properly set oauth token so perhaps not worth sharing, but let me know if you want something specific. These files are always synced across all of my devices, including phone, so I always have access to them.
</p>

<p>
That serves not just as data backup, but also as <b><b>data providers</b></b> for my tools. I only interact with these daily snapshots on filesystem rather than directly with API. That helps to avoid dealing with rate limiting, flakiness in network connection or API itself, and makes it way faster to iterate and develop. The only downside is that the data is not necessarily up to date, but perhaps you can dump data more often to get around this; I would still highly recommend you to prefer that to interacting with API directly. 
</p>

<p>
I'm using a <b><b>special Python package to access the data</b></b>, which I called <code>my</code>. It's always in my <code>PYTHONPATH</code> so I can use it from any script/tool or REPL. It's got bunch of different submodules, e.g. <code>my.reading.instapaper</code>, <code>my.reading.kobo</code>, <code>my.reading.polar</code> (there are other modules than <code>my.reading</code>, but that material for a whole separate post). The package itself is not public since it happens to have some personal data in it, at some point I'll try to strip it off and release it (not sure if it would be really relevant for other people anyway).
</p>
</div>


<div id="outline-container-org000002b" class="outline-3">
<h3 id="org000002b">Extracting reading stats</h3>
<div class="outline-text-3" id="text-org000002b">
<p>
As a specific example how I do it: recently my friend asked me if I could recommend them posts I found interesting on <a href="https://slatestarcodex.com/">Slate Star Codex</a>. With a tiny python script I was quickly able to give them some stats on posts I read, so they could choose among them.
</p>

<div class="org-src-container">
<pre class="src src-python">import my.reading.hypothesis
for p in my.reading.hypothesis.get_pages():
    if 'slatestarcodex' in p.link: 
	print(f'{p.link} {len(p.highlights)}')
</pre>
</div>
</div>
</div>

<div id="outline-container-org000002c" class="outline-3">
<h3 id="org000002c">Searching in annotations</h3>
<div class="outline-text-3" id="text-org000002c">
<p>
<a id="org0000000"></a>I've got bunch of scripts and a rendering tool which I named <a href="https://github.com/karlicoss/orger">orger</a> (yep, haven't invested that much thought into naming).
Basically, these scripts take specific data source as input and produce org-mode output, e.g. renders <code>json</code> backed up from Instapaper into <code>instapaper.org</code> file. That runs every few hours and keeps the contents relatively up to date.
</p>

<p>
I chose org-mode as I was already used to its features, keybindings and metadata. Also the hierarchy (e.g. book &rarr; highlight &rarr; comments) fits naturally into outline format. But not that it's a real necessity, I feel that as long as it's searchable plaintext, it's good enough.
</p>

<p>
To search them, I've got a <b><b>global keybinding</b></b>, which invokes Emacs with incremental search prompt against the directory with rendered <code>org</code> files, which lets me interact with them in a blink on my computer. On Android I'm using <a href="https://play.google.com/store/apps/details?id=com.docsearch">DocSearch</a> indexer (sadly it's not incremental, and app is not open source, so I'm looking for alternative).
</p>

<p>
Finally, I've got a <a href="https://www.lesbonscomptes.com/recoll">Recoll</a> indexer instance + web interface running on my VPS; so if necessary I can access and search annotations via the internet.
</p>
</div>
</div>

<div id="outline-container-org000002d" class="outline-3">
<h3 id="org000002d"><a id="org0000001"></a>Providing TODO items</h3>
<div class="outline-text-3" id="text-org000002d">
<p>
While reading, I often encounter something I want to google or check or read about later; or just come up to something actionable inspired by what I'm reading.
But I also don't want to interrupt from reading and losing context: that especially matters while reading on a E-ink device: distracting from the book, fetching your phone etc is really annoying.
</p>

<p>
So, as a workaround, I have programmed rules that pick out notes that start with "TODO" or marked with "TODO" tags; etc, and they are <b><b>automatically added to my agenda</b></b>. Later, when I see it on agenda, I'd assign it a priority and reschedule/unschedule depending on importance.
</p>

<p>
<a href="https://github.com/karlicoss/orger/blob/350e76000e34db49cf6b574041b98bd813040851/ip2org.py#L16">Here's</a> an example of me using using <code>my.instapaper</code> module for that.
</p>
</div>
</div>

<div id="outline-container-org000002e" class="outline-3">
<h3 id="org000002e"><a id="org0000002"></a>Spaced repetition</h3>
<div class="outline-text-3" id="text-org000002e">
<p>
It's kind of an extension of the previous use case: again, often you want to send something straight into your <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Spaced_repetition">spaced repetition</a> queue without having to remember to add that.
</p>

<p>
I've got two rules for that:
</p>

<ul class="org-ul">
<li>if something is annotated with a certain marker ('drill' for me, comes from <a href="https://orgmode.org/worg/org-contrib/org-drill.html">org-drill</a> package name)</li>
<li>if it's only got one word highlighted, which is useful for memorizing foreign words</li>
</ul>

<p>
<a href="https://github.com/karlicoss/orger/blob/350e76000e34db49cf6b574041b98bd813040851/krill.py#L13">Here's</a> how I'm using it for Kobo highlights.
</p>
</div>
</div>

<div id="outline-container-org000002f" class="outline-3">
<h3 id="org000002f">Life log</h3>
<div class="outline-text-3" id="text-org000002f">
<p>
I'm a big fan of <a class="post-tag" href="./tags.html#lifelogging">#lifelogging</a> and all the timestamped highlights, comments and <a href="#org000001e">reading progress</a> from Kobo are an effortless (no manual logging!) contribution to my personal timeline, which I render and sync on my devices every few hours.
</p>

<p>
I sometimes use it when conversation with other people comes to awkward silence, so I can recall something I was reading recently and spark off an interesting (well at least for me) topic.
</p>
</div>
</div>
</div>

<div id="outline-container-org0000031" class="outline-2">
<h2 id="org0000031"><span class="section-number-2">8</span> --</h2>
<div class="outline-text-2" id="text-8">
<p>
I'd be interested to know what do you think, and how are you managing your annotations or if you need some help with your existing workflow. Please also let me know if I missed any tools or features!
</p>
</div>
</div>

    </section>

    
    <section class="footer">
        <div class="post-tags"><a class="post-tag" href="./tags.html#pkm">#pkm</a> <a class="post-tag" href="./tags.html#annotation">#annotation</a> <a class="post-tag" href="./tags.html#sr">#sr</a> <a class="post-tag" href="./tags.html#tools">#tools</a></div>
        <!-- TODO post-date? -->
        <div class="date">05 July 2019</div>
    </section>
    

    <section class="comments">
    <script data-isso="https://beepb00p.xyz/comments/" data-isso-reply-to-self="true" src="https://beepb00p.xyz/comments/js/embed.min.js">
</script>

<section id="isso-thread" data-isso-id="isso_pkm_annotating"></section>

    </section>

</article>

        </main>

        <!-- TODO hmm maybe display something in a footer, so it's clear it's end of content... -->
        <footer>
        </footer>
    </body>
</html>
]]></description>
    <pubDate>Fri, 05 Jul 2019 00:00:00 UT</pubDate>
    <guid>https://beepb00p.xyz/annotating.html</guid>
    <dc:creator>karlicoss</dc:creator>
</item>
<item>
    <title>Don't shoot the artist</title>
    <link>https://beepb00p.xyz/contemp-art.html</link>
    <description><![CDATA[<!doctype html>
<html lang="en">
    <head>
        <meta charset="utf-8">
        <meta http-equiv="Content-Type" content="text/html; charset=UTF-8" />
        <meta http-equiv="x-ua-compatible" content="ie=edge">
        <meta name="viewport" content="width=device-width, initial-scale=1">

        <meta name="generator" content="hakyll">
        <meta name="language" content="English">
        
        <meta name="keywords" content="art">
        
        <!-- TODO concat with keywords tags; also need to make comma separated? -->

        <title>Don't shoot the artist | Mildly entertainingᵝ</title>

        <link rel="stylesheet" href="./css/default.css?v=2" />
        <link rel="stylesheet" href="./css/links.css?v=2" />

        <!-- TODO make it conditional on actually having math on page? -->
        <script type="text/javascript">
 window.MathJax = {
     tex2jax: {
         // note that hakyll source has got double dollar signs due to special meaning in templates
         inlineMath: [ ['$','$'], ["\\(","\\)"] ],
         processEscapes: true
     }
 };
</script>
<script async src="https://cdnjs.cloudflare.com/ajax/libs/mathjax/2.7.5/MathJax.js?config=TeX-AMS-MML_HTMLorMML"></script>

    </head>
    <body>
        <header>
            <nav>
                <span class="nav-left">
                    <a class="fat" href="./">Home</a>
                    <!-- TODO eh, not sure if this symbol is good for that... -->
                    ·
                    <a class="fat" href="./ideas.html">Ideas</a>
                    ·
                    <a class="fat" href="./notes.html">Notes</a>
                    ·
                    <a class="fat" href="./tags.html">Tags</a>
                </span>
                <span class="nav-right">
                    <a class="fat" href="./feed.html">Feed</a>
                    ·
                    <a class="fat" href="./site.html">Site</a>
                    ·
                    <a class="fat" href="./me.html">Me</a>
                </span>
            </nav>
        </header>

        <main>
            

<!-- <link rel="stylesheet" href="/css/org.css" /> -->
<link rel="stylesheet" href="./css/org-default.css" />

<link rel="stylesheet" href="./css/org-extra.css?v=2" />



<article>
    <section class="post-title">
    <h1>Don't shoot the artist</h1>
    <div class="summary">How I visited a contemporary art museum and didn't get it</h2>
    </section>
    <!-- are sections appropriate for that? -->

    <section class="content">
    <p>
Today I visited <a href="https://www.ludwigmuseum.hu/en">Ludwig Museum</a> in Budapest, which hosts a contemporary art gallery.
</p>

<p>
I don't think I generally 'get' contemporary art. However I don't get conventional either! I'm quite an unsophisticated person, some of art I like and appretiate, some don't. So I'm usually trying to expose myself to it just to keep up.
</p>

<p>
Anyway, by the time I got to the third floor of the exhibition I started to get irritated. Usually, I can appreciate at least some of art objects, but none of the ones I had seen so far made any sense. 
</p>

<p>
Some irritation was directed internally: "Ugh why am I doing this to myself, I should have gotten a coffee, sat on grass and enjoyed reading Penrose instead". But also a bit at the artists: "Ok, it's 2019, hasn't humanity seen enough white squares and various kinds of gradients?".
</p>

<p>
So as I walked among popart on the last floor my mind wandered and I remembered a post I read on <a href="https://slatestarcodex.com/2019/02/26/rule-genius-in-not-out/">SSC</a>. The idea that I had absorbed from it is that I shouldn't really judge people who are trying to come up with new ideas and things; they are already a minority and it's not worth wasting my mental resources as long as they are not harming anyone.
</p>

<p>
Perhaps it's similar with art? They are exploring new territory, new mediums, so they are quite likely to make mistakes, such as things very few people get, if not <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Shard">hated by many</a>.
But the 1% that does manage to push the boundary would result in something beautiful that no one else would otherwise make (I'm sure you fancy at least some contemporary <a href="https://www.huffpost.com/entry/2014-archdaily-building-of-the-year-awards_n_4645591">buildings</a> or <a href="https://www.tate.org.uk/visit/tate-modern">art works</a> unless you were born in 1830). 
</p>

<p>
Not sure what happens to the remaining 99%. Maybe they give up on trying to invent new art and just become decent designers/architects? Would be interesting to check if that's actually the case.
</p>

<p>
This realization made the irritation go and made the rest of exploration a bit more pleasurable.
</p>

    </section>

    
    <section class="footer">
        <div class="post-tags"><a class="post-tag" href="./tags.html#art">#art</a></div>
        <!-- TODO post-date? -->
        <div class="date">12 May 2019</div>
    </section>
    

    <section class="comments">
    <script data-isso="https://beepb00p.xyz/comments/" data-isso-reply-to-self="true" src="https://beepb00p.xyz/comments/js/embed.min.js">
</script>

<section id="isso-thread" data-isso-id="isso_contemp_art"></section>

    </section>

</article>

        </main>

        <!-- TODO hmm maybe display something in a footer, so it's clear it's end of content... -->
        <footer>
        </footer>
    </body>
</html>
]]></description>
    <pubDate>Sun, 12 May 2019 00:00:00 UT</pubDate>
    <guid>https://beepb00p.xyz/contemp-art.html</guid>
    <dc:creator>karlicoss</dc:creator>
</item>
<item>
    <title>I've found Google Takeouts to silently remove old data</title>
    <link>https://beepb00p.xyz/takeout-data-gone.html</link>
    <description><![CDATA[<!doctype html>
<html lang="en">
    <head>
        <meta charset="utf-8">
        <meta http-equiv="Content-Type" content="text/html; charset=UTF-8" />
        <meta http-equiv="x-ua-compatible" content="ie=edge">
        <meta name="viewport" content="width=device-width, initial-scale=1">

        <meta name="generator" content="hakyll">
        <meta name="language" content="English">
        
        <meta name="keywords" content="backup">
        
        <!-- TODO concat with keywords tags; also need to make comma separated? -->

        <title>I've found Google Takeouts to silently remove old data | Mildly entertainingᵝ</title>

        <link rel="stylesheet" href="./css/default.css?v=2" />
        <link rel="stylesheet" href="./css/links.css?v=2" />

        <!-- TODO make it conditional on actually having math on page? -->
        <script type="text/javascript">
 window.MathJax = {
     tex2jax: {
         // note that hakyll source has got double dollar signs due to special meaning in templates
         inlineMath: [ ['$','$'], ["\\(","\\)"] ],
         processEscapes: true
     }
 };
</script>
<script async src="https://cdnjs.cloudflare.com/ajax/libs/mathjax/2.7.5/MathJax.js?config=TeX-AMS-MML_HTMLorMML"></script>

    </head>
    <body>
        <header>
            <nav>
                <span class="nav-left">
                    <a class="fat" href="./">Home</a>
                    <!-- TODO eh, not sure if this symbol is good for that... -->
                    ·
                    <a class="fat" href="./ideas.html">Ideas</a>
                    ·
                    <a class="fat" href="./notes.html">Notes</a>
                    ·
                    <a class="fat" href="./tags.html">Tags</a>
                </span>
                <span class="nav-right">
                    <a class="fat" href="./feed.html">Feed</a>
                    ·
                    <a class="fat" href="./site.html">Site</a>
                    ·
                    <a class="fat" href="./me.html">Me</a>
                </span>
            </nav>
        </header>

        <main>
            




<article>
    <section class="post-title">
    <h1>I've found Google Takeouts to silently remove old data</h1>
    <div class="summary">Crosspost from /r/DataHoarder</h2>
    </section>
    <!-- are sections appropriate for that? -->

    <section class="content">
    <p>This is a <a href="https://www.reddit.com/r/DataHoarder/comments/ayt5cu/ive_found_out_google_takeout_archives_are_not/">crosspost</a> from Reddit.</p>
<p><strong>TLDR</strong>: keep/backup your old Google Takeout archives, turns out the data is not persisted across them.</p>
<p>So I am working on a personal project for which I am collecting all the URLs I even visited. I update them via cron from multiple sources, in particular my latest Google Takeout archive which I’m always storing on my desktop. I’ve been improving the resilience of the project in terms of making sure I don’t break URL extracion so I wrote a script to diff the extracted urls and check if any of them disappear. What I found out was that urls from takeout were in fact mysteriously disappearing.</p>
<p>After a bit of WTF and investigation, turned out that takeout data is not cumulative (at least for some of sources), and seems to have some sort of retention period.</p>
<p>Here are some of my findings:</p>
<ul>
<li><p>archive from 20181227</p>
<pre><code>  grep time_usec BrowserHistory.json | sort | head -n 3
            &quot;time_usec&quot;: 1513604826000563
            &quot;time_usec&quot;: 1513606272469876
            &quot;time_usec&quot;: 1513606362996796
  oldest entry is 18 Dec 2017

  tidy -q -i Chrome/MyActivity.html | grep -e 'PM' -e 'AM' | tail -n 3
            Dec 18, 2017, 2:12:42 PM UTC
            Dec 18, 2017, 2:11:12 PM UTC
            Dec 18, 2017, 1:47:06 PM UTC

  tidy -q -i Search/MyActivity.html | grep -e 'PM' -e 'AM' | tail -n 3
            Jan 23, 2015, 7:56:09 PM UTC
            Jan 23, 2015, 7:42:42 PM UTC
            Jan 23, 2015, 7:42:41 PM UTC</code></pre></li>
<li><p>archive from 20180623</p>
<pre><code>  grep time_usec BrowserHistory.json | sort | head -n 3
            &quot;time_usec&quot;: 1496659157550587
            &quot;time_usec&quot;: 1496660371451340
            &quot;time_usec&quot;: 1496661577902967
  oldest entry is 05 Jun 2017

  tidy -q -i Chrome/MyActivity.html | grep -e 'PM' -e 'AM' | tail -n 3 
            Jun 5, 2017, 2:43:58 PM
            Jun 5, 2017, 2:43:55 PM
            Jun 5, 2017, 2:40:28 PM

  tidy -q -i Search/MyActivity.html | grep -e 'PM' -e 'AM' | tail -n 3
            Aug 5, 2014, 6:19:32 PM
            Aug 5, 2014, 5:25:34 PM
            Aug 5, 2014, 5:25:32 PM</code></pre></li>
<li><p>archive from 20170410</p>
<pre><code>  grep time_usec BrowserHistory.json | sort | head -n 3
            &quot;time_usec&quot;: 1465298229733388
            &quot;time_usec&quot;: 1465298231949965
            &quot;time_usec&quot;: 1465298248753114
  oldest entry is 07 Jun 2016</code></pre>
<p>that takeout doesn’t have any of MyActivity.html (Google added it later in 2017) there is <code>Searches</code> directory which contains some jsons back to October 2010</p></li>
</ul>
<p>In summary: looks like <code>BrowserHistory.json</code> has got a retention of about 1 year, same for <code>Chrome/MyActivity.html</code>. <code>Search/MyActivity.html</code> has got a retention of about 3 years. It’s a mess.</p>
<p>Not sure if there is a similar issue with other takeout stuff (e.g. youtube watch history, shopping, location etc), so be careful if you rely on it!</p>
<p>I guess it was sort of a gut feeling that I was paranoid about that and was keeping some of the older archives.</p>
<p>Also I haven’t really found anything about this retention anywhere in google takeout FAQ. Does anyone know about it? Is it some sort of legal requirement, a bug or something else?</p>
    </section>

    
    <section class="footer">
        <div class="post-tags"><a class="post-tag" href="./tags.html#backup">#backup</a></div>
        <!-- TODO post-date? -->
        <div class="date">08 March 2019</div>
    </section>
    

    <section class="comments">
    <script data-isso="https://beepb00p.xyz/comments/" data-isso-reply-to-self="true" src="https://beepb00p.xyz/comments/js/embed.min.js">
</script>

<section id="isso-thread" data-isso-id="isso_takeout_data_gone"></section>

    </section>

</article>

        </main>

        <!-- TODO hmm maybe display something in a footer, so it's clear it's end of content... -->
        <footer>
        </footer>
    </body>
</html>
]]></description>
    <pubDate>Fri, 08 Mar 2019 00:00:00 UT</pubDate>
    <guid>https://beepb00p.xyz/takeout-data-gone.html</guid>
    <dc:creator>karlicoss</dc:creator>
</item>
<item>
    <title>Grasp</title>
    <link>https://beepb00p.xyz/grasp.html</link>
    <description><![CDATA[<!doctype html>
<html lang="en">
    <head>
        <meta charset="utf-8">
        <meta http-equiv="Content-Type" content="text/html; charset=UTF-8" />
        <meta http-equiv="x-ua-compatible" content="ie=edge">
        <meta name="viewport" content="width=device-width, initial-scale=1">

        <meta name="generator" content="hakyll">
        <meta name="language" content="English">
        
        <meta name="keywords" content="pkm org-capture annotation">
        
        <!-- TODO concat with keywords tags; also need to make comma separated? -->

        <title>Grasp | Mildly entertainingᵝ</title>

        <link rel="stylesheet" href="./css/default.css?v=2" />
        <link rel="stylesheet" href="./css/links.css?v=2" />

        <!-- TODO make it conditional on actually having math on page? -->
        <script type="text/javascript">
 window.MathJax = {
     tex2jax: {
         // note that hakyll source has got double dollar signs due to special meaning in templates
         inlineMath: [ ['$','$'], ["\\(","\\)"] ],
         processEscapes: true
     }
 };
</script>
<script async src="https://cdnjs.cloudflare.com/ajax/libs/mathjax/2.7.5/MathJax.js?config=TeX-AMS-MML_HTMLorMML"></script>

    </head>
    <body>
        <header>
            <nav>
                <span class="nav-left">
                    <a class="fat" href="./">Home</a>
                    <!-- TODO eh, not sure if this symbol is good for that... -->
                    ·
                    <a class="fat" href="./ideas.html">Ideas</a>
                    ·
                    <a class="fat" href="./notes.html">Notes</a>
                    ·
                    <a class="fat" href="./tags.html">Tags</a>
                </span>
                <span class="nav-right">
                    <a class="fat" href="./feed.html">Feed</a>
                    ·
                    <a class="fat" href="./site.html">Site</a>
                    ·
                    <a class="fat" href="./me.html">Me</a>
                </span>
            </nav>
        </header>

        <main>
            




<article>
    <section class="post-title">
    <h1>Grasp</h1>
    <div class="summary">How to capture information from your browser and stay sane</h2>
    </section>
    <!-- are sections appropriate for that? -->

    <section class="content">
    <p>This is not the post I was gonna start writing with. It was supposed to be something a bit more abstract and pure, but oh well.</p>
<p>Trigger warning: if you are a kind of person that doesn’t care about their browser bookmarks at all and happily loses them after switching to new computer, you might be shocked and perhaps repulsed by the level of elaboration I’m taking up here. Please sit tight, breathe and remember that I don’t judge you!</p>
<p>So, let’s talk about browser bookmarks.</p>
<h1 id="history">History</h1>
<p>I’ve always loved my bookmarks and been keeping, rereading and moving them around since high school. I also tend to be very organized in terms of meta information, so every bookmark would eventually end up in a category/folder. Of course there are obstacles.</p>
<p>First of all, Chromium bookmark adding menu was a bit shit and <a href="http://www.rawinfopages.com/tips/wp-content/uploads/2017/08/chrome-bookmarks1.png">still</a> is. You get to choose among the five most recently used folders only; if you want anything specific, you have to click all the way through (Tab with my 100+ folders was just not doable). You can’t search when you add bookmark either. Yes, I know, it’s not meant for geeks, it’s for normal people who love mouseclicks. I’m still puzzled by how people who develop that stuff use their own product though.</p>
<p>These days Chrome has got <code>chrome.bookmarks</code> api, which I’d imagine allows you to implement your own bookmark manager. Back in 2012, it didn’t exist though.</p>
<p>I was a bit less fussy back then so I was kind of okay with that. Until one day the disaster appended. I realized I couldn’t decide which folder did the bookmark belong to. That was pretty disturbing, so I started looking for alternatives. I realized I needed something like tags and turned out Firefox had that feature for ages. So I switched the browser.</p>
<p>Firefox was noticeably slower and greedier in terms of RAM (no Rust in Firefox in 2012!). And few months later I got my first Android phone and realized that Firefox didn’t support syncing tags with Android (it still <a href="https://bugzilla.mozilla.org/show_bug.cgi?id=775672">doesn’t</a>).</p>
<p>Until I found out about <a href="https://pinboard.in">Pinboard</a>! If you wanna borrow one thing from this post, please try and use that, it’s really awesome. It has solved almost all of my issues:</p>
<ul>
<li>you can easily add new bookmarks, tag them and it would be synced across all your browsers and devices</li>
<li>you can mark them private and public, and search in other people’s bookmarks</li>
<li>what is more, you can add notes for some context about your bookmarks!</li>
</ul>
<p>I’ve had few happy years with Pinboard. Until I started getting more serious about information processing and my knowledge management. I’ll tell about that one day, but long story short, I found out that I spend a lot of time moving bookmarks scattered across pinboard into my personal plaintext wiki to give it a bit more structure, fulltext search and easier access. I’ve also started using Org mode and in particular, <a href="https://orgmode.org/manual/Capture-Refile-Archive.html#Capture-Refile-Archive">capture and refile</a>. Once you are used to that, moving information manually by copy-pasting is just plain torture. You know, life is too short for that shit.</p>
<h1 id="eh-capture-refile">Eh? Capture? Refile?</h1>
<p>It’s hard to explain, for me it took several iterations to adopt these. In essence, you can ‘capture’, that is, copy/create piece of information like a url, quote, your thought or anything else and store in a text file for further processing which you can do it later. It’s meant to be with as little interruptions as possible, merely to persist the information. Typically, in emacs it’s a matter of pressing a keystroke, making you note and pressing a keystroke to finalize. You can do it as fast as you think/type and then immediately get back to what you were working on.</p>
<p>You can look up quite a few different setups online: <a href="https://youtu.be/fgizHHd7nOo?t=207">typical demo (till 4:10)</a>. The concept doesn’t really have to be restricted to org mode, though. Funny enough, before I ran into org-capture, I had a keybinding to open Vim in the insert mode against my <code>notes.txt</code> file.</p>
<h2 id="it-sounds-really-abstract.">It sounds really abstract.</h2>
<p>Sure. Let me be a bit more specific. My typical scenario is doing some research in the broad sense, e.g. shopping or looking for a property to rent or learning.</p>
<p>Imagine you’ve got a bit of time during your lunch break at work and want to spend it learning some <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Representation_theory">representation theory</a>. For me (and I’d imagine for many people), it makes little sense doing that just for 20 minutes, your mind is diffused, and you need time to gain back some context before doing productive learning.</p>
<p>But you could at least skim through some articles and highlight things to think about later when you got more time which you can dedicate solely for learning. So you read through the different articles and blog posts, and you want to highlight things and potentially add todo items for further googling/thinking. You don’t have time to think about them now, you just want to make sure you think about them later, e.g. see <a href="https://user-images.githubusercontent.com/291333/51799721-a984eb80-221c-11e9-9612-8eb7f553dc01.png">screenshot</a>.</p>
<p>So you go through the article and annotate it/add points to think on. You want to do it as fast as you can read without distracting on copy-pasting the information and trying to organize it. Later, when you got time, you just search everything marked with the tag <code>reprtheory</code> and in your <code>capture.org</code> file you find an entry like that:</p>
<pre><code>* [2019-02-09 Sat 14:54] Special unitary group - Wikipedia   :reprtheory:physics:
https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Special_unitary_group
Selection:
here is a 2:1 homomorphism from SU(2) to SO(3).
Comment:
Why do they always mention that? Is that important?</code></pre>
<p>, which you can further action on. Perhaps you’ve figured it out already, so you can just discard it. Or you want to convert it into a TODO, give it a priority and refile somewhere more appropriate. What’s awesome is that at the time of capture it immediately becomes searchable and indexable as any plaintext would without any extra effort (unlike if you added it to browser bookmarks/pinboard).</p>
<h1 id="ok-im-sold.-how-do-i-do-it">Ok, I’m sold. How do I do it?</h1>
<p>So, you want to integrate your browser with your knowledge repository and capture things straight into your <code>capture.org</code> file. Sounds trivial, right?</p>
<p>For a while I used <a href="https://github.com/sprig/org-capture-extension">org-capture extension</a>, that was relying on setting up a special mime type handler (e.g. <code>emacs://</code>) and an always running emacs daemon. Until one day I got very sad when few days of captured link and selected text were gone because one of these things stopped working for some reason. People seem to have issues setting up all this to work, and of course, you can’t have feedback from OS mime handler, so you can never know whether it has succeeded at all.</p>
<p>I realized I didn’t want to rely on emacs running all the time, on its templates or anything like that. I just want to reliably append stuff (formatted as org-mode) to the text file, that’s not too much to ask. An obvious solution is to get rid of the mime type handler and just write to the file system from Chrome extension directly. This is, of course something you can’t do in modern browsers. There is an <a href="https://developer.chrome.com/apps/app_storage#write">API</a> in Chrome for that, and you’ve got two options:</p>
<ul>
<li>write a file to a sandbox within a browser. Not an option for my purposes.</li>
<li>select a path via ‘save as’ GUI dialog and write it. Disgusting, <em>definitely</em> not an option.</li>
</ul>
<p>So after a while I realized something else has to write to the file. And that something else could be a local http server. The extension sends the request, the local backend writes the entry and responds with success/error, which can be passed onto UI notification, so you will always know if something failed. After a bit of coding, <a href="https://github.com/karlicoss/grasp">Grasp</a> was born.</p>
<h1 id="what-makes-grasp-better">What makes Grasp better?</h1>
<p>Quite a few things actually!</p>
<ul>
<li><p>it’s reliable and you will get an error notification if you failed to capture</p></li>
<li><p>it supports capturing selected text, adding comment and tags</p></li>
<li><p>you can capture anywhere: it doesn’t care whether you have emacs installed at all, and doesn’t have to be org mode file</p></li>
<li><p>unlike <a href="https://orgmode.org/manual/capture-protocol.html">org-protocol</a> which only supports url, title and ‘everything else’, the capture template syntax can be extended to include anything you want, e.g. <a href="https://github.com/karlicoss/grasp/blob/247dd5856d34d05f4c2239f34a5d2904d0961326/server/org_tools.py#L91">currently</a> it also supports <code>tags</code>, <code>comment</code> and <code>selection</code>.</p></li>
<li><p>it can run anywhere, e.g. you can run it the server on your VPS and access remotely if you are browsing on a computer you can’t sync your capture file onto.</p>
<p>I might even try and see if it can be ported as <a href="https://addons.mozilla.org/en-GB/android/">Android Firefox addon</a>.</p></li>
</ul>
<h1 id="implementing">Implementing</h1>
<p>Few random things I learnt while implementing:</p>
<ul>
<li><p><a href="https://flow.org">flow</a> and <a href="https://eslint.org/">eslint</a> are good</p>
<p>Trivial to integrate and they make the dreaded JS programming pretty manageable and akin to Python.</p>
<p>Turns out Flow even it supports <a href="https://flow.org/en/docs/types/comments/">comment types</a>, kinda like <a href="https://www.python.org/dev/peps/pep-0484/#type-comments">python/mypy</a>. That must be very beneficial for people trying to integrate it. Just imagine that you can slowly convert your whole codebase into type safe code before your coworkers realize what’s happened!</p></li>
<li><p>Webpack is good</p>
<p>Used it mainly to strip off Flow annotations and convert code into something chrome would accept. However it’s also helpful for merging the extension manifest so you could build browser-specific versions.</p></li>
<li><p>fun fact: <code>node_modules</code> takes almost 200Mb of disk space, and I tried my best to use as less dependencies as possible. Almost all are dev dependencies, so the extension itself is still tiny.</p></li>
<li><p>Firefox and Chrome use more or less same browser APIs these days! The only thing I had to fix while porting to Firefox were notifications.</p></li>
<li>publishing to Chrome store is more tedious than I imagined, e.g.
<ul>
<li>they want screenshots exactly 1280x800 or 640x400. Do people have some sort of scripts to cut their screenshots automatically for them or what?</li>
<li>there are two interfaces (‘old’ and ‘new’), which are sometimes doing different things</li>
<li>it’s generally pretty flaky, sometimes when you update the extension, old meta about your extension disappears and you have to copy it manually. I find it pretty mean to developers.</li>
</ul>
<p>I guess I should just use the <a href="https://developer.chrome.com/webstore/using_webstore_api">API</a> for publishing.</p></li>
<li><p>publishing to <a href>addons.mozilla.org</a> is super fast and easy</p></li>
<li><p><a href="https://github.com/karlicoss/grasp/issues/7">firefox hotkeys are not configurable</a></p>
<p>I still find it very hard to believe. Has it always been like that? How do people cope with it?</p></li>
<li><p>CI is a bit tedious</p>
<a href="https://github.com/karlicoss/grasp/blob/master/.circleci/config.yml">My pretty minimal config</a>, is quite long. I’m quite used to to CIs, but I wonder how often are people discouraged by that, it’s got to be easier. Perhaps <a href="https://docs.gitlab.com/ee/topics/autodevops/">Auto DevOps</a> from gitlab solves it?</li>
<li><p>communicating with <code>localhost</code> made everything so much simpler. I’ve already converted another <a href="https://github.com/karlicoss/were-you-here">thing</a> I am working on to use that instead of trying to utilize local storage/internal database and it works flawlessly!</p></li>
</ul>
<h1 id="feedback">Feedback</h1>
<p>I actually think it’s the first thing I solely implemented and prepared something and <a href="https://www.reddit.com/r/orgmode/comments/akazos/orggrasp_browser_extension_for_orgcapture/">shared</a> for other people to use. As expected, it actually took more time than sketching a prototype that worked for me. But it feels so great when people DM you on reddit and say that they managed to run it even on Windows without any issues when no other existing methods could do that.</p>
<h1 id="whats-next">What’s next?</h1>
<p>I’m gonna look up what are Markdown people using for capturing information, add few templates and spread the good stuff. I’m excited!</p>
    </section>

    
    <section class="footer">
        <div class="post-tags"><a class="post-tag" href="./tags.html#pkm">#pkm</a> <a class="post-tag" href="./tags.html#org-capture">#org-capture</a> <a class="post-tag" href="./tags.html#annotation">#annotation</a></div>
        <!-- TODO post-date? -->
        <div class="date">09 February 2019</div>
    </section>
    

    <section class="comments">
    <script data-isso="https://beepb00p.xyz/comments/" data-isso-reply-to-self="true" src="https://beepb00p.xyz/comments/js/embed.min.js">
</script>

<section id="isso-thread" data-isso-id="isso_org_grasp"></section>

    </section>

</article>

        </main>

        <!-- TODO hmm maybe display something in a footer, so it's clear it's end of content... -->
        <footer>
        </footer>
    </body>
</html>
]]></description>
    <pubDate>Sat, 09 Feb 2019 00:00:00 UT</pubDate>
    <guid>https://beepb00p.xyz/grasp.html</guid>
    <dc:creator>karlicoss</dc:creator>
</item>
<item>
    <title>Forcing IPython to display multiple equations in single line</title>
    <link>https://beepb00p.xyz/ipynb-singleline.html</link>
    <description><![CDATA[<!doctype html>
<html lang="en">
    <head>
        <meta charset="utf-8">
        <meta http-equiv="Content-Type" content="text/html; charset=UTF-8" />
        <meta http-equiv="x-ua-compatible" content="ie=edge">
        <meta name="viewport" content="width=device-width, initial-scale=1">

        <meta name="generator" content="hakyll">
        <meta name="language" content="English">
        
        <meta name="keywords" content="ipython emacs">
        
        <!-- TODO concat with keywords tags; also need to make comma separated? -->

        <title>Forcing IPython to display multiple equations in single line | Mildly entertainingᵝ</title>

        <link rel="stylesheet" href="./css/default.css?v=2" />
        <link rel="stylesheet" href="./css/links.css?v=2" />

        <!-- TODO make it conditional on actually having math on page? -->
        <script type="text/javascript">
 window.MathJax = {
     tex2jax: {
         // note that hakyll source has got double dollar signs due to special meaning in templates
         inlineMath: [ ['$','$'], ["\\(","\\)"] ],
         processEscapes: true
     }
 };
</script>
<script async src="https://cdnjs.cloudflare.com/ajax/libs/mathjax/2.7.5/MathJax.js?config=TeX-AMS-MML_HTMLorMML"></script>

    </head>
    <body>
        <header>
            <nav>
                <span class="nav-left">
                    <a class="fat" href="./">Home</a>
                    <!-- TODO eh, not sure if this symbol is good for that... -->
                    ·
                    <a class="fat" href="./ideas.html">Ideas</a>
                    ·
                    <a class="fat" href="./notes.html">Notes</a>
                    ·
                    <a class="fat" href="./tags.html">Tags</a>
                </span>
                <span class="nav-right">
                    <a class="fat" href="./feed.html">Feed</a>
                    ·
                    <a class="fat" href="./site.html">Site</a>
                    ·
                    <a class="fat" href="./me.html">Me</a>
                </span>
            </nav>
        </header>

        <main>
            
<link rel="stylesheet" href="./css/ipynb.css" />
<link rel="stylesheet" href="./css/ipynb-syntax.css" />




<article>
    <section class="post-title">
    <h1>Forcing IPython to display multiple equations in single line</h1>
    <div class="summary">How I sacrificed few hours of my life for aethetics</h2>
    </section>
    <!-- are sections appropriate for that? -->

    <section class="content">
    


   
   <details class="cell-collapsed">
   <summary>IPython imports <span class="cell-collapsed-expand">(click to expand)</span></summary>
       
<div class="cell border-box-sizing code_cell rendered">
<div class="input">
<div class="prompt input_prompt">In&nbsp;[1]:</div>
<div class="inner_cell">
    <div class="input_area">
<div class=" highlight hl-ipython3"><pre><span></span><span class="kn">from</span> <span class="nn">sympy</span> <span class="k">import</span> <span class="n">symbols</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="n">Derivative</span> <span class="k">as</span> <span class="n">D</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="n">Function</span> <span class="k">as</span> <span class="n">F</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="n">Eq</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="n">init_printing</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="n">latex</span>
<span class="kn">from</span> <span class="nn">IPython.display</span> <span class="k">import</span> <span class="n">Markdown</span>
<span class="n">init_printing</span><span class="p">()</span>
</pre></div>

    </div>
</div>
</div>

</div>
   </details>





    
<div class="cell border-box-sizing text_cell rendered"><div class="prompt input_prompt">
</div><div class="inner_cell">
<div class="text_cell_render border-box-sizing rendered_html">
<p>If you are working with numerical computations in an IPython notebook, you don't really have much choice but accompany your computations by Latex
formulas. However, with symbolic computations, you can massively save on repeating the same formulas which are already encoded in your
symbolic object. Here's a quick example how it typically looks in the notebooks I've seen on the internet:</p>
<hr>

</div>
</div>
</div>





    
<div class="cell border-box-sizing code_cell rendered">
<div class="input">
<div class="prompt input_prompt">In&nbsp;[2]:</div>
<div class="inner_cell">
    <div class="input_area">
<div class=" highlight hl-ipython3"><pre><span></span><span class="n">x</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="n">t</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="n">symbols</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="s1">'x t'</span><span class="p">)</span>
<span class="n">U</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="n">F</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="s1">'U'</span><span class="p">)(</span><span class="n">x</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="n">t</span><span class="p">)</span>
<span class="n">heat_eq</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="n">Eq</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">D</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">U</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="n">t</span><span class="p">),</span> <span class="n">D</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">U</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="n">x</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="mi">2</span><span class="p">))</span>
</pre></div>

    </div>
</div>
</div>

</div>





    
<div class="cell border-box-sizing text_cell rendered"><div class="prompt input_prompt">
</div><div class="inner_cell">
<div class="text_cell_render border-box-sizing rendered_html">
<p>Solving heat type PDE:</p>

</div>
</div>
</div>





    
<div class="cell border-box-sizing code_cell rendered">
<div class="input">
<div class="prompt input_prompt">In&nbsp;[3]:</div>
<div class="inner_cell">
    <div class="input_area">
<div class=" highlight hl-ipython3"><pre><span></span><span class="n">display</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">heat_eq</span><span class="p">)</span>
</pre></div>

    </div>
</div>
</div>

<div class="output_wrapper">
<div class="output">


<div class="output_area">

    <div class="prompt"></div>




<div class="output_latex output_subarea ">
$\displaystyle \frac{\partial}{\partial t} U{\left(x,t \right)} = \frac{\partial^{2}}{\partial x^{2}} U{\left(x,t \right)}$
</div>

</div>

</div>
</div>

</div>





    
<div class="cell border-box-sizing code_cell rendered">
<div class="input">
<div class="prompt input_prompt">In&nbsp;[4]:</div>
<div class="inner_cell">
    <div class="input_area">
<div class=" highlight hl-ipython3"><pre><span></span><span class="n">bc_left</span>  <span class="o">=</span> <span class="n">Eq</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">U</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="n">subs</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">x</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="mi">0</span><span class="p">),</span> <span class="mi">0</span><span class="p">)</span>
<span class="n">bc_right</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="n">Eq</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">U</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="n">subs</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">x</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="mi">1</span><span class="p">),</span> <span class="mi">0</span><span class="p">)</span>
</pre></div>

    </div>
</div>
</div>

</div>





    
<div class="cell border-box-sizing text_cell rendered"><div class="prompt input_prompt">
</div><div class="inner_cell">
<div class="text_cell_render border-box-sizing rendered_html">
<p>Subject to:</p>

</div>
</div>
</div>





    
<div class="cell border-box-sizing code_cell rendered">
<div class="input">
<div class="prompt input_prompt">In&nbsp;[5]:</div>
<div class="inner_cell">
    <div class="input_area">
<div class=" highlight hl-ipython3"><pre><span></span><span class="n">display</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">bc_left</span><span class="p">)</span>
<span class="n">display</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">bc_right</span><span class="p">)</span>
</pre></div>

    </div>
</div>
</div>

<div class="output_wrapper">
<div class="output">


<div class="output_area">

    <div class="prompt"></div>




<div class="output_latex output_subarea ">
$\displaystyle U{\left(0,t \right)} = 0$
</div>

</div>

<div class="output_area">

    <div class="prompt"></div>




<div class="output_latex output_subarea ">
$\displaystyle U{\left(1,t \right)} = 0$
</div>

</div>

</div>
</div>

</div>





    
<div class="cell border-box-sizing text_cell rendered"><div class="prompt input_prompt">
</div><div class="inner_cell">
<div class="text_cell_render border-box-sizing rendered_html">
<hr>
<p>What I don't like about that style of presentation is that it's pretty scattered and reqires interleaving displayed formulas with random python cells.
That's bad since it either pollutes your notebook and takes up vertical space, or discourages you from producing useful outputs in favor of notebook aethetics. Here are couple of examples <a href="https://www.sympy.org/en/index.html">featured on Sympy</a> website:</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://digitalcommons.calpoly.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1072&amp;context=physsp/">Quantum Programming in Python</a>, suffers from the first problem</li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/bjodah/chempy/blob/d5371c7/examples/ammonical_cupric_solution.ipynb">chempy</a> suffers from the second problem</li>
</ul>
<p>What we want is to output whole bunch of things at once.
Sadly, <code>display</code> doesn't support even outputting two formulas on a single line without hacking CSS,
so this is the easiest way of doing it I came up with to so far:</p>

</div>
</div>
</div>





    
<div class="cell border-box-sizing code_cell rendered">
<div class="input">
<div class="prompt input_prompt">In&nbsp;[6]:</div>
<div class="inner_cell">
    <div class="input_area">
<div class=" highlight hl-ipython3"><pre><span></span><span class="n">display</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">Markdown</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="s2">&quot;Solving heat type PDE $</span><span class="si">{}</span><span class="s2">$ subject to: $</span><span class="si">{}</span><span class="s2">$ and $</span><span class="si">{}</span><span class="s2">$&quot;</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="n">format</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">latex</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">heat_eq</span><span class="p">),</span> <span class="n">latex</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">bc_left</span><span class="p">),</span> <span class="n">latex</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">bc_right</span><span class="p">))))</span>
</pre></div>

    </div>
</div>
</div>

<div class="output_wrapper">
<div class="output">


<div class="output_area">

    <div class="prompt"></div>



<div class="output_markdown rendered_html output_subarea ">
<p>Solving heat type PDE $\frac{\partial}{\partial t} U{\left(x,t \right)} = \frac{\partial^{2}}{\partial x^{2}} U{\left(x,t \right)}$ subject to: $U{\left(0,t \right)} = 0$ and $U{\left(1,t \right)} = 0$</p>

</div>

</div>

</div>
</div>

</div>





    
<div class="cell border-box-sizing text_cell rendered"><div class="prompt input_prompt">
</div><div class="inner_cell">
<div class="text_cell_render border-box-sizing rendered_html">
<p>It's quite tedious to do that every time, so I extracted it in a little helper method:
TODO inject function code here... perhaps templating engine??</p>

</div>
</div>
</div>





    
<div class="cell border-box-sizing code_cell rendered">
<div class="input">
<div class="prompt input_prompt">In&nbsp;[7]:</div>
<div class="inner_cell">
    <div class="input_area">
<div class=" highlight hl-ipython3"><pre><span></span><span class="k">def</span> <span class="nf">ldisplay_md</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">fmt</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="o">*</span><span class="n">args</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="o">**</span><span class="n">kwargs</span><span class="p">):</span>
    <span class="n">display</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">Markdown</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">fmt</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="n">format</span><span class="p">(</span>
        <span class="o">*</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">f</span><span class="s1">'${latex(x)}$'</span> <span class="k">for</span> <span class="n">x</span> <span class="ow">in</span> <span class="n">args</span><span class="p">),</span>
        <span class="o">**</span><span class="p">{</span><span class="n">k</span><span class="p">:</span> <span class="n">f</span><span class="s1">'${latex(v)}$'</span> <span class="k">for</span> <span class="n">k</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="n">v</span> <span class="ow">in</span> <span class="n">kwargs</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="n">items</span><span class="p">()})</span>
    <span class="p">))</span>
</pre></div>

    </div>
</div>
</div>

</div>





    
<div class="cell border-box-sizing text_cell rendered"><div class="prompt input_prompt">
</div><div class="inner_cell">
<div class="text_cell_render border-box-sizing rendered_html">
<p>So far so good, I just define <code>ldisplay = ldisplay_md</code> on top of my notebook and use <code>ldisplay</code> instead of display for singleline outputs.</p>
<p>However while trying to use it with <a href="https://github.com/millejoh/emacs-ipython-notebook">EIN</a> (emacs frontent for jupiter),
I ran into an issue: EIN doesn't support Markdown outputs!
Same thing happens if you run it in terminal: you're just gonna get <code>&lt;IPython.core.display.Markdown object&gt;</code>.
Nevertheless, it is capable of outputing formulas as ASCII art, kinda like this:</p>

<pre><code>                2
∂              ∂
──(U(x, t)) = ───(U(x, t))
∂t              2
              ∂x

</code></pre>
<p>, so we can achieve a similar effect by formatting manually via <code>str.format</code>.</p>
<p>Without further ado, here's the bit of code which does that:</p>

</div>
</div>
</div>





    
<div class="cell border-box-sizing code_cell rendered">
<div class="input">
<div class="prompt input_prompt">In&nbsp;[8]:</div>
<div class="inner_cell">
    <div class="input_area">
<div class=" highlight hl-ipython3"><pre><span></span><span class="k">def</span> <span class="nf">as_text</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">thing</span><span class="p">):</span>
    <span class="kn">from</span> <span class="nn">IPython.core.interactiveshell</span> <span class="k">import</span> <span class="n">InteractiveShell</span> <span class="c1"># type: ignore</span>
    <span class="n">plain_formatter</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="n">InteractiveShell</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="n">instance</span><span class="p">()</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="n">display_formatter</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="n">formatters</span><span class="p">[</span><span class="s1">'text/plain'</span><span class="p">]</span>
    <span class="n">pp</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="n">plain_formatter</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">thing</span><span class="p">)</span>
    <span class="n">lines</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="n">pp</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="n">splitlines</span><span class="p">()</span>
    <span class="k">return</span> <span class="n">lines</span>

<span class="k">def</span> <span class="nf">vcpad</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">lines</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="n">height</span><span class="p">):</span>
    <span class="n">width</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="nb">len</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">lines</span><span class="p">[</span><span class="mi">0</span><span class="p">])</span>
    <span class="n">missing</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="n">height</span> <span class="o">-</span> <span class="nb">len</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">lines</span><span class="p">)</span>
    <span class="n">above</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="n">missing</span> <span class="o">//</span> <span class="mi">2</span>
    <span class="n">below</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="n">missing</span> <span class="o">-</span> <span class="n">above</span>
    <span class="k">return</span> <span class="p">[</span><span class="s1">' '</span> <span class="o">*</span> <span class="n">width</span> <span class="k">for</span> <span class="n">_</span> <span class="ow">in</span> <span class="nb">range</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">above</span><span class="p">)]</span> <span class="o">+</span> <span class="n">lines</span> <span class="o">+</span> <span class="p">[</span><span class="s1">' '</span> <span class="o">*</span> <span class="n">width</span> <span class="k">for</span> <span class="n">_</span> <span class="ow">in</span> <span class="nb">range</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">below</span><span class="p">)]</span>

<span class="c1"># terminal and emacs can't display markdown, so we have to use that as a workaround</span>
<span class="k">def</span> <span class="nf">mdisplay_plain</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">fmt</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="o">*</span><span class="n">args</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="o">**</span><span class="n">kwargs</span><span class="p">):</span>
    <span class="kn">import</span> <span class="nn">re</span>
    <span class="kn">from</span> <span class="nn">itertools</span> <span class="k">import</span> <span class="n">chain</span>
    <span class="n">fargs</span>   <span class="o">=</span> <span class="p">[</span><span class="n">as_text</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">a</span><span class="p">)</span> <span class="k">for</span> <span class="n">a</span> <span class="ow">in</span> <span class="n">args</span><span class="p">]</span>
    <span class="n">fkwargs</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="p">{</span><span class="n">k</span><span class="p">:</span> <span class="n">as_text</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">v</span><span class="p">)</span> <span class="k">for</span> <span class="n">k</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="n">v</span> <span class="ow">in</span> <span class="n">kwargs</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="n">items</span><span class="p">()}</span>

    <span class="n">height</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="nb">max</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="nb">len</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">x</span><span class="p">)</span> <span class="k">for</span> <span class="n">x</span> <span class="ow">in</span> <span class="n">chain</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">fargs</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="n">fkwargs</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="n">values</span><span class="p">()))</span>

    <span class="n">pargs</span>   <span class="o">=</span> <span class="p">[</span><span class="n">vcpad</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">a</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="n">height</span><span class="p">)</span> <span class="k">for</span> <span class="n">a</span> <span class="ow">in</span> <span class="n">fargs</span><span class="p">]</span>
    <span class="n">pkwargs</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="p">{</span><span class="n">k</span><span class="p">:</span> <span class="n">vcpad</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">v</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="n">height</span><span class="p">)</span> <span class="k">for</span> <span class="n">k</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="n">v</span> <span class="ow">in</span> <span class="n">fkwargs</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="n">items</span><span class="p">()}</span>

    <span class="n">textpos</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="n">height</span> <span class="o">//</span> <span class="mi">2</span>

    <span class="n">lines</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="p">[]</span>
    <span class="k">for</span> <span class="n">h</span> <span class="ow">in</span> <span class="nb">range</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">height</span><span class="p">):</span>
        <span class="n">largs</span>   <span class="o">=</span> <span class="p">[</span><span class="n">a</span><span class="p">[</span><span class="n">h</span><span class="p">]</span> <span class="k">for</span> <span class="n">a</span> <span class="ow">in</span> <span class="n">pargs</span><span class="p">]</span>
        <span class="n">lkwargs</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="p">{</span><span class="n">k</span><span class="p">:</span> <span class="n">v</span><span class="p">[</span><span class="n">h</span><span class="p">]</span> <span class="k">for</span> <span class="n">k</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="n">v</span> <span class="ow">in</span> <span class="n">pkwargs</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="n">items</span><span class="p">()}</span>
        <span class="k">if</span> <span class="n">h</span> <span class="o">==</span> <span class="n">textpos</span><span class="p">:</span>
            <span class="n">fstr</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="n">fmt</span>
        <span class="k">else</span><span class="p">:</span>
            <span class="c1"># we want to keep the formatting specifiers (stuff in curly braces and empty everything else)</span>
            <span class="n">fstr</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="s2">&quot;&quot;</span>
            <span class="k">for</span> <span class="n">e</span> <span class="ow">in</span> <span class="n">re</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="n">finditer</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="sa">r</span><span class="s1">'{.*?}'</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="n">fmt</span><span class="p">):</span>
                <span class="n">fstr</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="n">fstr</span> <span class="o">+</span> <span class="s2">&quot; &quot;</span> <span class="o">*</span> <span class="p">(</span><span class="n">e</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="n">start</span><span class="p">()</span> <span class="o">-</span> <span class="nb">len</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">fstr</span><span class="p">))</span>
                <span class="n">fstr</span> <span class="o">+=</span> <span class="n">e</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="n">group</span><span class="p">()</span>
        <span class="n">lines</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="n">append</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">fstr</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="n">format</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="o">*</span><span class="n">largs</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="o">**</span><span class="n">lkwargs</span><span class="p">))</span>
    <span class="k">for</span> <span class="n">line</span> <span class="ow">in</span> <span class="n">lines</span><span class="p">:</span>
        <span class="nb">print</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">line</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="n">rstrip</span><span class="p">())</span>
</pre></div>

    </div>
</div>
</div>

</div>





    
<div class="cell border-box-sizing code_cell rendered">
<div class="input">
<div class="prompt input_prompt">In&nbsp;[9]:</div>
<div class="inner_cell">
    <div class="input_area">
<div class=" highlight hl-ipython3"><pre><span></span><span class="n">mdisplay_plain</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="s2">&quot;Solving heat type PDE  </span><span class="si">{}</span><span class="s2"> subject to: </span><span class="si">{bl}</span><span class="s2"> and </span><span class="si">{br}</span><span class="s2">&quot;</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="n">heat_eq</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="n">bl</span><span class="o">=</span><span class="n">bc_left</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="n">br</span><span class="o">=</span><span class="n">bc_right</span><span class="p">)</span>
</pre></div>

    </div>
</div>
</div>

<div class="output_wrapper">
<div class="output">


<div class="output_area">

    <div class="prompt"></div>


<div class="output_subarea output_stream output_stdout output_text">
<pre>                                       2
                       ∂              ∂
Solving heat type PDE  ──(U(x, t)) = ───(U(x, t)) subject to: U(0, t) = 0 and U(1, t) = 0
                       ∂t              2
                                     ∂x
</pre>
</div>
</div>

</div>
</div>

</div>





    
<div class="cell border-box-sizing text_cell rendered"><div class="prompt input_prompt">
</div><div class="inner_cell">
<div class="text_cell_render border-box-sizing rendered_html">
<p>Neat? I think so!</p>
<p>The sad thing is that figuring out the <code>as_text</code> bit took me about an hour of intense debugging, 
including setting explicit pdb breakpoints in IPython source code. I'm not sure how normal people are meant to figure that out. 
One could argue that desire to work with IPython notebooks in Emacs is not very normal either though.
Hopefully that saves someone else a bit of time.</p>

</div>
</div>
</div>



 


    </section>

    
    <section class="footer">
        <div class="post-tags"><a class="post-tag" href="./tags.html#ipython">#ipython</a> <a class="post-tag" href="./tags.html#emacs">#emacs</a></div>
        <!-- TODO post-date? -->
        <div class="date">14 April 2019</div>
    </section>
    

    <section class="comments">
    <script data-isso="https://beepb00p.xyz/comments/" data-isso-reply-to-self="true" src="https://beepb00p.xyz/comments/js/embed.min.js">
</script>

<section id="isso-thread" data-isso-id="isso_ipynb_singleline"></section>

    </section>

</article>

        </main>

        <!-- TODO hmm maybe display something in a footer, so it's clear it's end of content... -->
        <footer>
        </footer>
    </body>
</html>
]]></description>
    <pubDate>Sun, 14 Apr 2019 00:00:00 UT</pubDate>
    <guid>https://beepb00p.xyz/ipynb-singleline.html</guid>
    <dc:creator>karlicoss</dc:creator>
</item>
<item>
    <title>How I extend my mind and cope with having fleshy human brain</title>
    <link>https://beepb00p.xyz/pkm-setup.html</link>
    <description><![CDATA[<!doctype html>
<html lang="en">
    <head>
        <meta charset="utf-8">
        <meta http-equiv="Content-Type" content="text/html; charset=UTF-8" />
        <meta http-equiv="x-ua-compatible" content="ie=edge">
        <meta name="viewport" content="width=device-width, initial-scale=1">

        <meta name="generator" content="hakyll">
        <meta name="language" content="English">
        
        <meta name="keywords" content="pkm org-mode learning">
        
        <!-- TODO concat with keywords tags; also need to make comma separated? -->

        <title>How I extend my mind and cope with having fleshy human brain | Mildly entertainingᵝ</title>

        <link rel="stylesheet" href="./css/default.css?v=2" />
        <link rel="stylesheet" href="./css/links.css?v=2" />

        <!-- TODO make it conditional on actually having math on page? -->
        <script type="text/javascript">
 window.MathJax = {
     tex2jax: {
         // note that hakyll source has got double dollar signs due to special meaning in templates
         inlineMath: [ ['$','$'], ["\\(","\\)"] ],
         processEscapes: true
     }
 };
</script>
<script async src="https://cdnjs.cloudflare.com/ajax/libs/mathjax/2.7.5/MathJax.js?config=TeX-AMS-MML_HTMLorMML"></script>

    </head>
    <body>
        <header>
            <nav>
                <span class="nav-left">
                    <a class="fat" href="./">Home</a>
                    <!-- TODO eh, not sure if this symbol is good for that... -->
                    ·
                    <a class="fat" href="./ideas.html">Ideas</a>
                    ·
                    <a class="fat" href="./notes.html">Notes</a>
                    ·
                    <a class="fat" href="./tags.html">Tags</a>
                </span>
                <span class="nav-right">
                    <a class="fat" href="./feed.html">Feed</a>
                    ·
                    <a class="fat" href="./site.html">Site</a>
                    ·
                    <a class="fat" href="./me.html">Me</a>
                </span>
            </nav>
        </header>

        <main>
            

<!-- <link rel="stylesheet" href="/css/org.css" /> -->
<link rel="stylesheet" href="./css/org-default.css" />

<link rel="stylesheet" href="./css/org-extra.css?v=2" />



<article>
    <section class="post-title">
    <h1>How I extend my mind and cope with having fleshy human brain</h1>
    <div class="summary">My personal knowledge setup</h2>
    </section>
    <!-- are sections appropriate for that? -->

    <section class="content">
    <p>
So, what is <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Personal_knowledge_management">personal knowledge management</a>? TLDR, it's a name for the process of organizing your tasks, thoughts, information you know, so a fairly useful concept.
</p>

<p>
I guess almost everyone at least at some point of their life tried to bring more organization: used a calendar, checklists, notebook etc.
Perhaps you also were learning something and were wondering of more efficient ways of memorizing, organizing and acting on that information.
</p>

<p>
This is what I'm loosely going to refer as PKM further on.
</p>

<p>
Some of the reasons what I'm going to write about might be useful to you:
</p>

<ul class="org-ul">
<li>you generally want to be more organized in your life but not sure how</li>
<li>you are reading lots of stuff, but then you feel like you quickly forget it (especially on the Internet, where information is denser than in books)</li>
<li>you think that flesh is weak and want to offload remembering things to external persistent medium</li>
</ul>

<p>
I'm writing that because my 'system' has more or less settled and stabilized, and I feel that I could be useful by helping out other people and sharing the ideas.
</p>

<p>
At this point, it also starts getting hard to keep up with all the things and hacks I implemented and maintaining let alone improving them, so I need to spread my ideas to the community.
</p>

<p>
A bit of disclaimer: some of the things I am doing may seem excessive and tedious &ndash; but you don't have to use exactly the same setup, I'm merely sharing for you something to kick off!
My own setup has been molded throughout the years with many influences from different people (who I will try to credit as long as I recall). Often some things I'm trying seem like too much effort even for me, but if you never overshoot, you might never hit that sweet spot between efficiency and convenience.
</p>

<p>
I'm very happy to discuss if you have any questions/suggestions/etc.
</p>

<style>
/* TODO err... what if it's got less than 2 digits?... so far only matters for pkm-plan post */
.section-number-2 {
    display: inline-block;
    text-align: right;
    width: 2ch;
}

/* TODO remove it later */
.todo {
  width: 4ch;
}

.outline-2 h2 {
/* TODO make a bit more spacious */
   margin-top: 0.1em;
   margin-bottom: 0.1em;
}
</style>

So, this is the plan, which I will fill with links as I write.

<div id="outline-container-org0000000" class="outline-2">
<h2 id="org0000000"><span class="section-number-2">1</span> <span class="todo TODO">TODO</span> task/todo management</h2>
</div>
<div id="outline-container-org0000001" class="outline-2">
<h2 id="org0000001"><span class="section-number-2">2</span> <span class="todo TODO">TODO</span> personal wiki</h2>
</div>

<div id="outline-container-org0000002" class="outline-2">
<h2 id="org0000002"><span class="section-number-2">3</span> <span class="todo TODO">TODO</span> searching</h2>
</div>
<div id="outline-container-org0000003" class="outline-2">
<h2 id="org0000003"><span class="section-number-2">4</span> <span class="todo TODO">TODO</span> logging and capturing</h2>
</div>

<div id="outline-container-org0000004" class="outline-2">
<h2 id="org0000004"><span class="section-number-2">5</span> <span class="todo TODO">TODO</span> processing captured content</h2>
</div>

<div id="outline-container-org0000005" class="outline-2">
<h2 id="org0000005"><span class="section-number-2">6</span> <a href="./annotating.html">Annotating content</a></h2>
<div class="outline-text-2" id="text-6">
</div>
</div>
<div id="outline-container-org0000006" class="outline-2">
<h2 id="org0000006"><span class="section-number-2">7</span> <span class="todo TODO">TODO</span> discovering new information</h2>
</div>

<div id="outline-container-org0000007" class="outline-2">
<h2 id="org0000007"><span class="section-number-2">8</span> <span class="todo TODO">TODO</span> spaced repetition and habits</h2>
</div>
<div id="outline-container-org0000008" class="outline-2">
<h2 id="org0000008"><span class="section-number-2">9</span> <span class="todo TODO">TODO</span> syncing</h2>
</div>

<div id="outline-container-org0000009" class="outline-2">
<h2 id="org0000009"><span class="section-number-2">10</span> <span class="todo TODO">TODO</span> regular backups</h2>
</div>
<div id="outline-container-org000000a" class="outline-2">
<h2 id="org000000a"><span class="section-number-2">11</span> <span class="todo TODO">TODO</span> timeline</h2>
</div>
<div id="outline-container-org000000b" class="outline-2">
<h2 id="org000000b"><span class="section-number-2">12</span> <span class="todo TODO">TODO</span> future</h2>
</div>

<div id="outline-container-org000000c" class="outline-2">
<h2 id="org000000c"><span class="section-number-2">13</span> <span class="todo TODO">TODO</span> developing tools</h2>
</div>

    </section>

    
    <section class="footer">
        <div class="post-tags"><a class="post-tag" href="./tags.html#pkm">#pkm</a> <a class="post-tag" href="./tags.html#org-mode">#org-mode</a> <a class="post-tag" href="./tags.html#learning">#learning</a></div>
        <!-- TODO post-date? -->
        <div class="date">13 May 2019</div>
    </section>
    

    <section class="comments">
    <script data-isso="https://beepb00p.xyz/comments/" data-isso-reply-to-self="true" src="https://beepb00p.xyz/comments/js/embed.min.js">
</script>

<section id="isso-thread" data-isso-id="isso_pkm_setup"></section>

    </section>

</article>

        </main>

        <!-- TODO hmm maybe display something in a footer, so it's clear it's end of content... -->
        <footer>
        </footer>
    </body>
</html>
]]></description>
    <pubDate>Mon, 13 May 2019 00:00:00 UT</pubDate>
    <guid>https://beepb00p.xyz/pkm-setup.html</guid>
    <dc:creator>karlicoss</dc:creator>
</item>
<item>
    <title>Quantifying quantified-mind.com</title>
    <link>https://beepb00p.xyz/quantified-mind.html</link>
    <description><![CDATA[<!doctype html>
<html lang="en">
    <head>
        <meta charset="utf-8">
        <meta http-equiv="Content-Type" content="text/html; charset=UTF-8" />
        <meta http-equiv="x-ua-compatible" content="ie=edge">
        <meta name="viewport" content="width=device-width, initial-scale=1">

        <meta name="generator" content="hakyll">
        <meta name="language" content="English">
        
        <meta name="keywords" content="cognitive quantified-self selenium">
        
        <!-- TODO concat with keywords tags; also need to make comma separated? -->

        <title>Quantifying quantified-mind.com | Mildly entertainingᵝ</title>

        <link rel="stylesheet" href="./css/default.css?v=2" />
        <link rel="stylesheet" href="./css/links.css?v=2" />

        <!-- TODO make it conditional on actually having math on page? -->
        <script type="text/javascript">
 window.MathJax = {
     tex2jax: {
         // note that hakyll source has got double dollar signs due to special meaning in templates
         inlineMath: [ ['$','$'], ["\\(","\\)"] ],
         processEscapes: true
     }
 };
</script>
<script async src="https://cdnjs.cloudflare.com/ajax/libs/mathjax/2.7.5/MathJax.js?config=TeX-AMS-MML_HTMLorMML"></script>

    </head>
    <body>
        <header>
            <nav>
                <span class="nav-left">
                    <a class="fat" href="./">Home</a>
                    <!-- TODO eh, not sure if this symbol is good for that... -->
                    ·
                    <a class="fat" href="./ideas.html">Ideas</a>
                    ·
                    <a class="fat" href="./notes.html">Notes</a>
                    ·
                    <a class="fat" href="./tags.html">Tags</a>
                </span>
                <span class="nav-right">
                    <a class="fat" href="./feed.html">Feed</a>
                    ·
                    <a class="fat" href="./site.html">Site</a>
                    ·
                    <a class="fat" href="./me.html">Me</a>
                </span>
            </nav>
        </header>

        <main>
            




<article>
    <section class="post-title">
    <h1>Quantifying quantified-mind.com</h1>
    <div class="summary">Exploiting javascript to reverse engineer cognitive score</h2>
    </section>
    <!-- are sections appropriate for that? -->

    <section class="content">
    <p><a href="http://www.quantified-mind.com/about">Quantified Mind</a> is a website which provides a handful of cognitive tests. It lets you choose a bunch of tests and you can run them whenever you wish, adding quantitative variables you are measuring alongside (e.g. hours of sleep, or cups of coffee you drank) or just arbitrary notes. <a href="http://quantifiedself.com/wp-content/uploads/2012/04/QM_collage.jpg">Here</a> is how it looks like.</p>
<p>Why is it interesting? If you are like me and don’t feel much obvious subjective effects of conventional stimulants, sleep or exercise, it would be great to have some objective measure in case the effects are subtle but present. For you it could be saving half an hour of sleep per night by using melatonin, or realizing coffee doesn’t have effect on your cognitive performance, or something else.</p>
<p>That sounded pretty interesting to me, and I started doing some tests (simple reaction time, visual matching, sorting and 1-back). However, given that effects are subtle in the first place, I wasn’t expecting to get any insights by gazing at collected data, so I needed to make sure I can export my experiments to run some sort of regression on them later.</p>
<p>To my disappointment, when I ran thirty or something sessions and downloaded the CSV, it didn’t have error rate/reaction time, but you are only getting some magical ‘score’. It was unclear what it meant from the FAQ so I emailed the authors and got a response:</p>
<pre><code>As for scores - it's a calculation that involves everything in a test, so for simple reaction time it involves both reaction times
and accuracy. 
The actual formulas aren't available, but the instructions are always simple: go for accuracy first, and try to be as fast as you can
without sacrificing accuracy.</code></pre>
<p>“Formulas aren’t available” was quite unsatisfactory to me. What are they actually measuring? So before carrying on and doing more tests I tried to reverse engineer the model.</p>
<h1 id="implementation">Implementation</h1>
<p>The idea was simple: choose couple of tests that are easy to automate. Luckily, the website is not using flash and not very heavy on javascript or obfuscation, so interacting with elements via javascript was fairly easy. In essence, I’m varying average reaction time (delay) and number of errors (which I make deliberately in the script), and inject the script into chrome via Selenium. Then I record the scores for further analysis.</p>
<p>If you wanna experiment by yourself, <a href="https://github.com/karlicoss/qm-reverse-engineering">here’s</a> the repository and if you don’t feel like running the scripts for a day to collect data, I uploaded it to <a href="https://github.com/karlicoss/qm-reverse-engineering/releases">releases</a>.</p>
<h1 id="tests">Tests</h1>
<p>I’ve chosen “Simple reaction time” and “Visual matching”. From the <a href="http://www.quantified-mind.com/science">“science”</a> section:</p>
<pre><code>The first is “Simple Reaction Time,” which assesses how quickly a person can respond to a single stimulus (a circle that turns 
from white to green) by pressing the space bar. 

“Visual Matching” places two highlighted grids next to one another and asks a person to judge, as quickly as possible, whether 
the two grids are identical.</code></pre>
<h1 id="results">Results</h1>
<p>TLDR: I find the models pretty weird.</p>
<p>Here is the demo of my script that extracted scores from the tests: <iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/dolS7X7QrB0" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen></iframe></p>
<p>Here is what I got after the simulations (clicking highly recommended):</p>
<p><a href="https://user-images.githubusercontent.com/291333/53916603-6a875880-405a-11e9-9447-90da86bf959a.png"> <img src="https://user-images.githubusercontent.com/291333/53916603-6a875880-405a-11e9-9447-90da86bf959a.png" width="auto" /> </a></p>
<p><a href="https://user-images.githubusercontent.com/291333/53916604-6a875880-405a-11e9-824a-ab2445cc4184.png"> <img src="https://user-images.githubusercontent.com/291333/53916604-6a875880-405a-11e9-824a-ab2445cc4184.png" width="auto" /> </a></p>
<h1 id="observations">Observations</h1>
<ul>
<li><p>Same score could mean different things; you can see it from the plots if you draw horizontal lines, they would intersect multiple curves corresponding to different delays.</p>
<p>So, for instance, if you get score 600 on visual matching, that could mean that you did the test with 880ms reaction and 0 errors, or with 840ms reaction and 2 errors or 760ms reaction and 4 errors. These are fairly different results and even though it’s good to have some sort of aggregate score, it’s also useful to distinguish. E.g. maybe caffeine makes you less patient so you press early and make more errors.</p></li>
<li><p>For low reaction time (&lt;300ms for simple reaction time &lt;600ms for visual matching), the plots don’t look continuous, there are some sudden drops. That’s pretty suspicious IMO.</p>
<p>Perhaps that could explained by the fact that such low times are impossible to get by average humans and they are out of the test domain.</p></li>
<li><p>If you keep number of error fixed, one would expect that score grows as the reaction time goes does. That is not the case on plots, probably related to the artifact above.</p></li>
<li><p>If you keep reaction time fixed, you would expect the score to decrease monotonically with the number of errors. You can see that for simple reaction time after 600ms, the score actually monotonically <strong>increases</strong> as you make more errors. Again, one could argue that reaction of 600 ms is too long for average human on this test (e.g. I score about 230), but I can easily imagine drugs (even such as alcohol) resulting in these scores, which could also be interesting to measure.</p></li>
<li><p>If you think about, 8 (out of 16) errors is what you would get on visual matching if you answer randomly (which you could do with almost arbitrary low reaction time). So if you do that, say, with 400ms delay, according to the plot you would score around 620 points. Which is what I get by doing the test myself with 800ms reaction and making 1 error. So what does the score represent then?</p></li>
</ul>
<h1 id="summary">Summary</h1>
<p>I can’t see how is that score meaningful and I’m glad I didn’t spend more time doing these tests. Perhaps one is better off measuring reaction time directly instead of some mystical ‘score’.</p>
<h1 id="whats-next">What’s next?</h1>
<p>Could be interesting to do similar reverse engineering on other cognitive testing platforms.</p>
    </section>

    
    <section class="footer">
        <div class="post-tags"><a class="post-tag" href="./tags.html#cognitive">#cognitive</a> <a class="post-tag" href="./tags.html#quantified-self">#quantified-self</a> <a class="post-tag" href="./tags.html#selenium">#selenium</a></div>
        <!-- TODO post-date? -->
        <div class="date">06 March 2019</div>
    </section>
    

    <section class="comments">
    <script data-isso="https://beepb00p.xyz/comments/" data-isso-reply-to-self="true" src="https://beepb00p.xyz/comments/js/embed.min.js">
</script>

<section id="isso-thread" data-isso-id="isso_quantified_mind"></section>

    </section>

</article>

        </main>

        <!-- TODO hmm maybe display something in a footer, so it's clear it's end of content... -->
        <footer>
        </footer>
    </body>
</html>
]]></description>
    <pubDate>Wed, 06 Mar 2019 00:00:00 UT</pubDate>
    <guid>https://beepb00p.xyz/quantified-mind.html</guid>
    <dc:creator>karlicoss</dc:creator>
</item>
<item>
    <title>On cognitive demand of recycling</title>
    <link>https://beepb00p.xyz/recycling-is-hard.html</link>
    <description><![CDATA[<!doctype html>
<html lang="en">
    <head>
        <meta charset="utf-8">
        <meta http-equiv="Content-Type" content="text/html; charset=UTF-8" />
        <meta http-equiv="x-ua-compatible" content="ie=edge">
        <meta name="viewport" content="width=device-width, initial-scale=1">

        <meta name="generator" content="hakyll">
        <meta name="language" content="English">
        
        <meta name="keywords" content="recycling environment">
        
        <!-- TODO concat with keywords tags; also need to make comma separated? -->

        <title>On cognitive demand of recycling | Mildly entertainingᵝ</title>

        <link rel="stylesheet" href="./css/default.css?v=2" />
        <link rel="stylesheet" href="./css/links.css?v=2" />

        <!-- TODO make it conditional on actually having math on page? -->
        <script type="text/javascript">
 window.MathJax = {
     tex2jax: {
         // note that hakyll source has got double dollar signs due to special meaning in templates
         inlineMath: [ ['$','$'], ["\\(","\\)"] ],
         processEscapes: true
     }
 };
</script>
<script async src="https://cdnjs.cloudflare.com/ajax/libs/mathjax/2.7.5/MathJax.js?config=TeX-AMS-MML_HTMLorMML"></script>

    </head>
    <body>
        <header>
            <nav>
                <span class="nav-left">
                    <a class="fat" href="./">Home</a>
                    <!-- TODO eh, not sure if this symbol is good for that... -->
                    ·
                    <a class="fat" href="./ideas.html">Ideas</a>
                    ·
                    <a class="fat" href="./notes.html">Notes</a>
                    ·
                    <a class="fat" href="./tags.html">Tags</a>
                </span>
                <span class="nav-right">
                    <a class="fat" href="./feed.html">Feed</a>
                    ·
                    <a class="fat" href="./site.html">Site</a>
                    ·
                    <a class="fat" href="./me.html">Me</a>
                </span>
            </nav>
        </header>

        <main>
            




<article>
    <section class="post-title">
    <h1>On cognitive demand of recycling</h1>
    <div class="summary">So many questions, so few answers</h2>
    </section>
    <!-- are sections appropriate for that? -->

    <section class="content">
    <p>Even since I moved to the UK I’ve of course been separating waste. I wasn’t ever questioning the positive value of recycling or suspecting it could be a conspiracy designed to drain my time or anything along that line. In many ways it’s even easier since you can pile up plastic/cardboard/glass and just throw it away in bulk, and have a smaller food waste bin. I was never too crazy about it though, so I never bothered recycling every last bit of material that I possibly could.</p>
<p>Recently though I started wondering if I should be more efficient at recycling, so I googled for a bit, and … got nowhere.</p>
<p>For instance, one of my fluorescent light bulbs died. It’s not recycled by the council, so can’t be put in the recycling dumpster. Apparently it also contains mercury and shouldn’t be put in general waste either. The closest recycling facility that accepts energy efficient bulbs is 15 mins from me by tube. The question is — disregarding that I don’t feel like spending half an hour in transport to recycle couple of light bulbs: is it more efficient for the planet if instead of going there I just spend that time on my high paying job and donate the money. I seriously suspect that recycling a bulb is <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Effective_altruism">not the most environmentally efficient thing I can do with my skills</a>. <strong>How much environmental impact in terms of pure dollars of damage does a light bulb have anyway?</strong> Sadly, I didn’t manage to find any specific numbers.</p>
<p>Another thing that puzzled me: <strong>is it worth washing a soiled plastic container before recycling?</strong> You’re wasting hot water and detergents after all, which also has some environmental impact (also your time if you wash manually). The internet gives confusing answers, starting from people who put their greasy plastic in dishwasher to suggestions to only give a quick rinse. I can’t understand how rinsing without washing helps against attracting bacteria and greasing paper in mixed recycling. Couldn’t google anything meaningful either.</p>
<p>Interesting enough, while looking that up, I ran into many discussions of using paper plates vs washing ceramic plates — apparently it’s unclear which is more environmental! <a href="https://sustainability.stackexchange.com/a/6020">Here’s</a> an example calculation which gives <code>$0.78</code> vs <code>$0.63</code>, the difference I find pretty marginal. Generally all over the place the answer seems to be “it depends on your detergent, electricity source, etc”. <strong>How is an average person meant to figure that out?</strong></p>
<p>Lastly, it’s not even clear which <a href="https://www.pureplanetrecycling.co.uk/types-of-plastics/">types of plastic</a> materials you can recycle. For instance, my <a href="https://www.towerhamlets.gov.uk/lgnl/environment_and_waste/recycling_and_waste/a-z_recycling_guide.aspx">council’s website</a> has no mention of specific materials whatsoever, only ‘trays’, ‘yogurt pots’ and ‘bags’.</p>
<p><a href="https://www.cityoflondon.gov.uk/services/environment-and-planning/waste-and-recycling/household-waste-and-recycling/Pages/recycling-A-to-Z.aspx">City of London website</a> confuses me as well:</p>
<ul>
<li>It mentions PS (polystyrene, 6) as non-recyclable and it instructs to recycle yogurt pots. However some of yogurt pots are made of polystyrene!</li>
<li>“Plastic bags, including those used for salad, bread, rice/pasta should be placed in the household waste”. While most of salad packaging I seen here has no marking, some of it is made of PP (polypropylene, 5), which is same stuff that used to make yogurt pots. <strong>Surely there should be no difference in recycling as long as it’s the same material?</strong></li>
</ul>
<p>I find it very hard to remember every specific shape of plastic, surely it’s way easier to base your decision to recycle on a single number they but on plastic? At least there is a little I can do about that and I emailed my council asking to clarify.</p>
<p>Lastly, I can’t help feeling that I’m nitpicking and the 95% of obviously recyclable stuff I already recycle is enough; and that I should have spent time writing this post doing something more obviously useful. However, I’m already done and hopefully will gain more knowledge about recycling as a result.</p>
<p><strong>How can we make it easier to decide if something can or can’t be recycled and whether it has net positive cost with respect to time you spend doing it?</strong></p>
<p>If you know answers to any of the questions here, please let me know!</p>
    </section>

    
    <section class="footer">
        <div class="post-tags"><a class="post-tag" href="./tags.html#recycling">#recycling</a> <a class="post-tag" href="./tags.html#environment">#environment</a></div>
        <!-- TODO post-date? -->
        <div class="date">18 April 2019</div>
    </section>
    

    <section class="comments">
    <script data-isso="https://beepb00p.xyz/comments/" data-isso-reply-to-self="true" src="https://beepb00p.xyz/comments/js/embed.min.js">
</script>

<section id="isso-thread" data-isso-id="isso_recycling_is_hard"></section>

    </section>

</article>

        </main>

        <!-- TODO hmm maybe display something in a footer, so it's clear it's end of content... -->
        <footer>
        </footer>
    </body>
</html>
]]></description>
    <pubDate>Thu, 18 Apr 2019 00:00:00 UT</pubDate>
    <guid>https://beepb00p.xyz/recycling-is-hard.html</guid>
    <dc:creator>karlicoss</dc:creator>
</item>
<item>
    <title>Sleep tracking</title>
    <link>https://beepb00p.xyz/sleep-tracking.html</link>
    <description><![CDATA[<!doctype html>
<html lang="en">
    <head>
        <meta charset="utf-8">
        <meta http-equiv="Content-Type" content="text/html; charset=UTF-8" />
        <meta http-equiv="x-ua-compatible" content="ie=edge">
        <meta name="viewport" content="width=device-width, initial-scale=1">

        <meta name="generator" content="hakyll">
        <meta name="language" content="English">
        
        <meta name="keywords" content="sleep quantified-self">
        
        <!-- TODO concat with keywords tags; also need to make comma separated? -->

        <title>Sleep tracking | Mildly entertainingᵝ</title>

        <link rel="stylesheet" href="./css/default.css?v=2" />
        <link rel="stylesheet" href="./css/links.css?v=2" />

        <!-- TODO make it conditional on actually having math on page? -->
        <script type="text/javascript">
 window.MathJax = {
     tex2jax: {
         // note that hakyll source has got double dollar signs due to special meaning in templates
         inlineMath: [ ['$','$'], ["\\(","\\)"] ],
         processEscapes: true
     }
 };
</script>
<script async src="https://cdnjs.cloudflare.com/ajax/libs/mathjax/2.7.5/MathJax.js?config=TeX-AMS-MML_HTMLorMML"></script>

    </head>
    <body>
        <header>
            <nav>
                <span class="nav-left">
                    <a class="fat" href="./">Home</a>
                    <!-- TODO eh, not sure if this symbol is good for that... -->
                    ·
                    <a class="fat" href="./ideas.html">Ideas</a>
                    ·
                    <a class="fat" href="./notes.html">Notes</a>
                    ·
                    <a class="fat" href="./tags.html">Tags</a>
                </span>
                <span class="nav-right">
                    <a class="fat" href="./feed.html">Feed</a>
                    ·
                    <a class="fat" href="./site.html">Site</a>
                    ·
                    <a class="fat" href="./me.html">Me</a>
                </span>
            </nav>
        </header>

        <main>
            




<article>
    <section class="post-title">
    <h1>Sleep tracking</h1>
    <div class="summary">How not to do it</h2>
    </section>
    <!-- are sections appropriate for that? -->

    <section class="content">
    <p>I’ve been tracking my sleep passively for a while. Not that I had any issues with sleep, but considering you spend massive chunk of your life sleeping, seems like a good idea to optimize it. After I bought <a href="https://www.emfit.com/sleep-sensing-solutions-with-hrv">Emfit</a> sleep tracker I figured it would be interesting to try correlating its stats with my subjective feelings.</p>
<p>Every morning, I log few things on the scale from 0 (bad) to 2 (good), one of which is something that I defined as “physical energy” (as opposed to mental energy). Well,</p>
<pre><code>| date         | physical |
|              | energy   |
|--------------|----------+
| [2018-07-10] |        1 |
| [2018-07-11] |        1 |
| [2018-07-13] |        0 |
| [2018-07-15] |        1 |
| [2018-07-16] |        1 |
| [2018-07-17] |        1 |
| [2018-07-18] |        1 |
| [2018-07-19] |        1 |
| [2018-07-20] |        1 |
| [2018-07-21] |        1 |
| [2018-07-22] |        1 |
| [2018-07-23] |        1 |
| [2018-07-24] |        1 |
| [2018-07-27] |        1 |
| [2018-07-28] |        1 |
| [2018-07-31] |        1 |
| [2018-08-01] |        1 |
| [2018-08-02] |        1 |
| [2018-08-05] |        1 |
| [2018-08-07] |        1 |
| [2018-08-08] |        1 |
| [2018-08-09] |        1 |
| [2018-08-10] |        1 |
| [2018-08-13] |        1 |
| [2018-08-14] |        1 |
... you get the idea ...
| [2019-02-10] |        1 |
| [2019-02-11] |        1 |
| [2019-02-12] |        1 |
| [2019-02-13] |        1 |
| [2019-02-14] |        1 |
| [2019-02-15] |        1 |
| [2019-02-16] |        1 |
| [2019-02-17] |        1 |
| [2019-02-18] |        1 |
| [2019-01-19] |        1 |
| [2019-02-20] |        1 |</code></pre>
<p>As you can see that’s not very fruitful (not sure what happened on 13 July 2018 lol). There are two possibilities here: my self introspection is really bad: many well being/mood tracking apps would let people estimate on the scale from 1 to 10, and I can’t even distinguish between three states.</p>
<p>Another one is that I’m just very stable and actually have no variation. For instance, I never had problems working out first thing in the morning, without having any food or stimulants. What bothers me a bit is that I don’t seem to experience any ‘high energy’ states either, which apparently people do.</p>
<p>I guess the lesson here is to reevaluate things I’m measuring after a short while and make sure I can actually track something meaningful or something I am capable of measuring.</p>
    </section>

    
    <section class="footer">
        <div class="post-tags"><a class="post-tag" href="./tags.html#sleep">#sleep</a> <a class="post-tag" href="./tags.html#quantified-self">#quantified-self</a></div>
        <!-- TODO post-date? -->
        <div class="date">21 February 2019</div>
    </section>
    

    <section class="comments">
    <script data-isso="https://beepb00p.xyz/comments/" data-isso-reply-to-self="true" src="https://beepb00p.xyz/comments/js/embed.min.js">
</script>

<section id="isso-thread" data-isso-id="isso_sleep_tracking"></section>

    </section>

</article>

        </main>

        <!-- TODO hmm maybe display something in a footer, so it's clear it's end of content... -->
        <footer>
        </footer>
    </body>
</html>
]]></description>
    <pubDate>Thu, 21 Feb 2019 00:00:00 UT</pubDate>
    <guid>https://beepb00p.xyz/sleep-tracking.html</guid>
    <dc:creator>karlicoss</dc:creator>
</item>
<item>
    <title>sufs</title>
    <link>https://beepb00p.xyz/sufs.html</link>
    <description><![CDATA[<!doctype html>
<html lang="en">
    <head>
        <meta charset="utf-8">
        <meta http-equiv="Content-Type" content="text/html; charset=UTF-8" />
        <meta http-equiv="x-ua-compatible" content="ie=edge">
        <meta name="viewport" content="width=device-width, initial-scale=1">

        <meta name="generator" content="hakyll">
        <meta name="language" content="English">
        
        <meta name="keywords" content="tools setup">
        
        <!-- TODO concat with keywords tags; also need to make comma separated? -->

        <title>sufs | Mildly entertainingᵝ</title>

        <link rel="stylesheet" href="./css/default.css?v=2" />
        <link rel="stylesheet" href="./css/links.css?v=2" />

        <!-- TODO make it conditional on actually having math on page? -->
        <script type="text/javascript">
 window.MathJax = {
     tex2jax: {
         // note that hakyll source has got double dollar signs due to special meaning in templates
         inlineMath: [ ['$','$'], ["\\(","\\)"] ],
         processEscapes: true
     }
 };
</script>
<script async src="https://cdnjs.cloudflare.com/ajax/libs/mathjax/2.7.5/MathJax.js?config=TeX-AMS-MML_HTMLorMML"></script>

    </head>
    <body>
        <header>
            <nav>
                <span class="nav-left">
                    <a class="fat" href="./">Home</a>
                    <!-- TODO eh, not sure if this symbol is good for that... -->
                    ·
                    <a class="fat" href="./ideas.html">Ideas</a>
                    ·
                    <a class="fat" href="./notes.html">Notes</a>
                    ·
                    <a class="fat" href="./tags.html">Tags</a>
                </span>
                <span class="nav-right">
                    <a class="fat" href="./feed.html">Feed</a>
                    ·
                    <a class="fat" href="./site.html">Site</a>
                    ·
                    <a class="fat" href="./me.html">Me</a>
                </span>
            </nav>
        </header>

        <main>
            




<article>
    <section class="post-title">
    <h1>sufs</h1>
    <div class="summary">Tool to merge directories via symlinks</h2>
    </section>
    <!-- are sections appropriate for that? -->

    <section class="content">
    <p><a href="https://github.com/karlicoss/sufs">sufs</a> is a tool for ‘merging’ multiple directories into one via symlinks.</p>
<p>I’m syncing most of my stuff via syncthing, but some of it has to be locally (mainly for stupid reasons like massive <code>node_modules</code> directory etc.). But it’s nice to have a unified view of them so you don’t have to memorize what did you put where.</p>
<p>Usage example:</p>
<pre><code>   # initialize merged dir`
   mkdir /home/user/datas 

   # you might want to keep the following in cron
   sufs.py --to /home/user/datas /home/user/syncthing/data /home/user/dropbox/data /home/user/syncthing/data</code></pre>
<p>Before I wrote this script I tried FUSE based filesystems: <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/UnionFS">Unionfs</a> and <a href="https://github.com/trapexit/mergerfs">Mergerfs</a>, but wasn’t really satisfied. Weirdly, couldn’t also find anythig existing on github, so had to write my own.</p>
<p>First, you don’t know where actually fuse mounted dirst reside. Second, for instance, mergerfs had some weird new file handling logic, so the directories would end up scattered across multiple sources. Overall I found it a bit confusing.</p>
<p>This script uses symlinks, so you always know the actual location; and also maintains the top level directory as read only, so you can’t end up with dangling directories.</p>
<p>The only disadvantage at the moment is that symlink updating can only happen once a minute if you run via cron, but should be easy to use inotify if that’s an issue.</p>
    </section>

    
    <section class="footer">
        <div class="post-tags"><a class="post-tag" href="./tags.html#tools">#tools</a> <a class="post-tag" href="./tags.html#setup">#setup</a></div>
        <!-- TODO post-date? -->
        <div class="date">09 May 2019</div>
    </section>
    

    <section class="comments">
    <script data-isso="https://beepb00p.xyz/comments/" data-isso-reply-to-self="true" src="https://beepb00p.xyz/comments/js/embed.min.js">
</script>

<section id="isso-thread" data-isso-id="isso_sufs"></section>

    </section>

</article>

        </main>

        <!-- TODO hmm maybe display something in a footer, so it's clear it's end of content... -->
        <footer>
        </footer>
    </body>
</html>
]]></description>
    <pubDate>Thu, 09 May 2019 00:00:00 UT</pubDate>
    <guid>https://beepb00p.xyz/sufs.html</guid>
    <dc:creator>karlicoss</dc:creator>
</item>

    </channel>
</rss>
